<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Mischief of cabals, or, The faction expos'd with some considerations for a lasting settlement : in a letter to a member of Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50993</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13644701</idno>
  <idno type="VID">100905</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240849486</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17062</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13644701</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 795:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Mischief of cabals, or, The faction expos'd with some considerations for a lasting settlement : in a letter to a member of Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100905:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100905:1"/>
            <p>The Mischief of CABALS: OR, THE Faction Expos'd. WITH SOME CONSIDERATIONS FOR A <hi>Lasting Settlement,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a LETTER to a MEMBER of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <q>I know no Resolutions more worthy a Christian King, than to prefer his Conscience before his Kingdoms. <bibl>K. <hi>Charles 1. Eikon Basil. c. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:100905:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100905:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD you known how averse I have always been from ripping up old <hi>Sores,</hi> or hitting others on the <hi>Teeth</hi> with their past <hi>Miscarriages,</hi> when they promise to grow wiser and mend their <hi>Manners,</hi> you wou'd not, I am confident, have impos'd upon me so ungrateful a <hi>Task,</hi> as the giving you an <hi>account</hi> of the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Proceedings</hi> of some of our late <hi>pretended Patriots,</hi> which promoted, if not occasion'd, the <hi>Tragical Scene</hi> like to have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, had not <hi>Providence</hi> miraculously interpos'd.</p>
            <p>But when you assure me, 'tis not only convenient, but very necessary for the Publick Service, in the present posture of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to expose to the World the <hi>fatal Consequences</hi> of <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Cabals,</hi> and the <hi>unwarrantable Resolutions</hi> of a prevailing part of the <hi>Commons</hi> in our two last <hi>Parliaments,</hi> that others may thereby take warning to avoid that unhappy <hi>Rock,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Predecessors have so unluckily split; this <hi>powerful Charm,</hi> which shall ever Influence all the <hi>Actions</hi> of my <hi>Life,</hi> together with the <hi>weight</hi> of your own <hi>Commands,</hi> have forc'd me at last to a <hi>complyance.</hi> And tho' for the most part, this Subject has been already handled by several <hi>Pens,</hi> and particularly by the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Lawyer Outlaw'd,</hi> who made it his business to shew by several Reasons and Arguments, besides divers <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> and a great many <hi>Presidents</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> that as the <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealousies</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> were <hi>groundless</hi> and <hi>imaginary,</hi> so the <hi>Resolutions</hi> of the <hi>Leading Members</hi> at that time were <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary</hi> and <hi>Illegal,</hi> contrary to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Laws</hi> of the <hi>Nation:</hi> Yet at your request, since the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> were pleas'd to get their <hi>Votes</hi> Printed, by way of an <hi>Appeal</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> I will amongst others briefly offer you my Thoughts upon the matter, but after some few preliminaries, will begin mine where that <hi>Gentleman</hi> ended his <hi>Discourse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You remember, I suppose, what a <hi>Noise,</hi> what a <hi>Bustle</hi> has
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100905:3"/> been made with contriv'd <hi>Stories,</hi> and continual <hi>Alarums</hi> of <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conspiracies</hi> upon our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> like the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Hannibal ad Portas,</hi> when there was no danger of either; and what a stir they kept with their <hi>tumultuous Petitions</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dresses</hi> from all the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Republicans</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> in <hi>Winter</hi> 79. for the <hi>Parliaments</hi> sitting, which alone they thought was able to cure this <hi>Maladie imaginaire:</hi> And yet when the <hi>Parliament</hi> met, and sat long enough to have redress'd all the reall <hi>Grievances</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> our Worthy Patriots ev'n left us in a worse condition than they found us. The late <hi>King</hi> of ever blessed Memory, whom <hi>God</hi> has taken from an <hi>ungrateful Generation</hi> that was not worthy of him, to Reign with himself in <hi>Glory,</hi> offer'd them a great deal more than Subjects ought in duty to expect from their <hi>Soveraign;</hi> yet nothing but the very <hi>unhinging</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> by that <hi>Antimonarchical</hi> project the <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Exclusion,</hi> wou'd in any measure satisfie their <hi>Ambition.</hi> The <hi>Loyal Gentlemen</hi> of the <hi>Country,</hi> who dutifully obey'd their <hi>Princes Lawful Proclamation,</hi> were toss'd from <hi>Post</hi> to <hi>Pillar</hi> by their <hi>Catchpoles,</hi> and their <hi>Ban-Dogs,</hi> as <hi>Traytors</hi> to the <hi>People,</hi> and kept several Weeks under a tedious and chargeable <hi>confinement,</hi> without the lest <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> or Colour of <hi>Justice:</hi> And at the same time <hi>Sidney</hi> and <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and all the <hi>Republican</hi> Gang of 41. who were skulking abroad ever since his late <hi>Majesties</hi> most happy <hi>Restauration,</hi> flock'd home with all possible expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and were the great <hi>Favourites</hi> of our <hi>Leading Members.</hi> But it was certainly a very <hi>Comical</hi> passage how civilly they treated Mr. <hi>William Stawell,</hi> one of their <hi>Abhorrers,</hi> who had the courage to disobey their <hi>unwarrantable Summons,</hi> and tell their <hi>Messenger,</hi> if he did any thing contrary to <hi>Law,</hi> he wou'd an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer for't, as the <hi>Law</hi> directs, in the same <hi>County,</hi> where the Fact was committed. The <hi>Leading Members</hi> were so puzled at this unexpected <hi>Answer,</hi> that they knew neither how to digest nor revenge so great an <hi>affront,</hi> while Mr. <hi>Stawell</hi> had so much <hi>Law</hi> of his side; yet thinking it absolutely necessary to find out some <hi>Sham</hi> or other to blind the World, lest this shou'd be made a <hi>Leading Card</hi> for others to slight their pretended <hi>Authority,</hi> they very obligingly Voted the <hi>Gentleman</hi> sick, and unable to appear before them; and therefore were pleas'd to allow him a months time for his <hi>appearance.</hi> Votes 4. <hi>December</hi> 1680.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100905:3"/>
            <p>But this, and (if you except the grand <hi>project</hi> of <hi>Exclusion</hi>) all the other tricks and devices they made use of for eleven Weeks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to <hi>enflame</hi> and <hi>distract</hi> the <hi>People,</hi> seem'd but a <hi>Flea-bite,</hi> if compar'd with the <hi>unparallell'd Votes</hi> they pass'd some days before they forc'd the <hi>King</hi> to a <hi>Prorogation:</hi> When <hi>Sampson</hi>-like, who by pulling down the <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>House,</hi> destroy'd more <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> on the day of his <hi>Death,</hi> than in his whole <hi>Life</hi> before, they did more mischief by shaking the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> the three last days of their sitting, than in all the rest of their turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved,</hi> (say they) <hi>That His Majesty in His last Message, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving assured this House of his readiness to concur in all other means, for the preservation of the Protestant Religion; This House doth declare, that until a Bill be likewise passed for Excluding the D. of</hi> York, <hi>this House cannot give any supply to His Majesty, without danger to His Majesties Person, extream hazard of the Protestant Religion, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulness to those by whom this House is entrusted.</hi> Votes 7th <hi>Jan.</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>In this Vote we may observe with some Astonishment the great <hi>Condescensions</hi> of a <hi>Gracious Prince,</hi> and the ungrateful <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns</hi> of a <hi>stubborn People,</hi> who got a <hi>knack,</hi> of late days, to stand upon such <hi>trucking</hi> and <hi>bartering</hi> with their <hi>Soveraign,</hi> as their <hi>Predecessors</hi> durst not have offer'd in former Ages. Once indeed they presum'd on the <hi>Ʋsurpation</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> 4. who, because of his unjust Title, they thought wou'd deny them nothing: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Second Year of his <hi>Reign, The Commons desired they might have Answer of their Petitions before the gift of any Subsidy;</hi> to which the King answer'd, <hi>He would conferr with the Lords, and do what should be best, according to their Advice.</hi> And the last day of the Parliament He gave this Answer, <hi>That that manner of doing had not been seen nor used in no time of His Progenitors or Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, that they should have any Answer of their Petitions, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, before they have shewed and finished all their other bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness of Parliament, be it of any Grant, Business, or otherwise: And therefore the King would not in any ways change the good Customs and Ʋsages made and used of ancient times.</hi> But now, it seems, the case is alter'd, and <hi>No Cure, No Money,</hi> is always the Bargain.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100905:4"/> The <hi>King</hi> proffers to concurr with them in all other <hi>Expedients</hi> for their security, without any Limitation or Restriction, against the groundless <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealousies</hi> they pretended; but the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen-Moghen</hi> scorn'd to accept of any thing He cou'd safely consent to: And therefore when His Majesty press'd them to think of a <hi>supply</hi> for the <hi>relief</hi> of <hi>Tangier,</hi> they, as became such <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Dutiful Subjects,</hi> flatly refus'd it, because of the <hi>apparent Danger</hi> it threatn'd to His <hi>Majesties Person,</hi> and to the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> if the <hi>Moors</hi> were beaten upon their own <hi>Dunghill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus all <hi>Expedients</hi> are quite out of doors, and Voted not only <hi>insufficient,</hi> but <hi>dangerous;</hi> and no care must be taken to rescue <hi>Tangier</hi> out of the hands of <hi>Barbarians,</hi> for fear of <hi>hazarding</hi> His <hi>Majesties Person,</hi> and the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> by weakning the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Interest: No <hi>regard</hi> to the <hi>growing Greatness</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> nor the least thought of securing a distracted <hi>Nation</hi> from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs of so potent an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and not a <hi>Groat</hi> to be given for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Wellfare</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> without the forbidden fruit, the <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Exclusion.</hi> And so hot they were upon this <hi>unlucky scent,</hi> that like <hi>Aesop</hi>'s <hi>Dog</hi> in the <hi>Manger,</hi> they wou'd neither give any Money themselves, to supply the <hi>Kings urgent Necessities,</hi> and to maintain his <hi>Credit</hi> (wherein was contain'd that of the whole <hi>Nation</hi>) either at home or abroad, nor as much as in them lay, suffer others to part with any; to which purpose, least the <hi>Purse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strings</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> which they kept very close, shou'd chance to fail them, they bethought themselves of an <hi>enchanted Padlock,</hi> never before made use of, for their further <hi>Security;</hi> and to that end they pass'd the following Vote.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, That whosoever shall lend, or cause to be lent by way of advance, any Money upon the branches of the Kings Revenue, arising by Customs, Excise, or Hearth-Money, shall be adjug'd to hinder the sitting of Parliaments, and shall be responsable for the same in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> Votes ibid.</p>
            <p>But why should <hi>Subjects</hi> be condemn'd of this <hi>Bug-bear Crime,</hi> for lending the <hi>King</hi> their own <hi>Money</hi> upon a <hi>valuable Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</hi> Or why <hi>forejudg'd</hi> by the House of <hi>Commons,</hi> who never had the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Judicature?</hi> What, are we gone back again to <hi>Forty One,</hi> to be thus <hi>hag-ridden</hi> a second time? or can we be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100905:4"/> thought altogether so <hi>stupid,</hi> as to have forgot the <hi>Tyrannical Ʋsage</hi> we then receiv'd from a pack of <hi>Villains,</hi> that call'd themselves the House of <hi>Commons,</hi> and thought their <hi>Nemine Contradicente</hi> was enough to avoid both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Gospel?</hi> No Sir, <hi>A burnt Child dreads the Fire;</hi> and the <hi>Nation</hi> having by a <hi>dear bought-Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> open'd their <hi>Eyes,</hi> are of late more afraid of their <hi>fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Ʋsurpation,</hi> than ever they have been of the <hi>Princes Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> And therefore this <hi>Ʋnwarrantable Vote</hi> signified no more, but to let the <hi>People</hi> know what they might expect from such <hi>Patriots,</hi> if they had kept any longer in the <hi>Saddle;</hi> since they had as much <hi>Power</hi> to get all the <hi>Money</hi> of <hi>England</hi> into their <hi>Custody and Disposal,</hi> as to make it <hi>Penal</hi> in any one to dispose of his own, as he pleas'd. But let us hear their <hi>last Speech</hi> and <hi>Confession</hi> on the happy day of their <hi>Prorogation,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor'd many an <hi>Honest Man</hi> to his <hi>Liberty,</hi> and the <hi>Nation</hi> to some interval of <hi>Tranquillity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, that whosoever advised his Majesty to prorogue this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to any other purpose than in order to the passing of a Bill for the Exclusion of the Duke of</hi> York, <hi>is a Betrayer of the King, the Protestant Religion, and of the Kingdom of</hi> England; <hi>a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of the</hi> French <hi>Interest, and a Pensioner to</hi> France. <hi>Votes</hi> 10. Jan. 1680.</p>
            <p>This is but the old <hi>Cant</hi> in a new Dress, and the refin'd <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of <hi>Billinsgate Oratours,</hi> who always think it the best <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy to cry Whore first,</hi> the better to stop the mouths of their <hi>Adversaries.</hi> But I appeal to any Man of common <hi>Sense,</hi> if these very Men, even at that time, were not the <hi>grand Promoters</hi> of the <hi>French Interest,</hi> and consequently <hi>Pensioners to France.</hi> For had that <hi>Politick Monarch</hi> employ'd so many <hi>Agents</hi> into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> 'tis plain he cou'd not have pitch'd on a surer <hi>way</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his <hi>Designs,</hi> than the dividing and distracting the <hi>People</hi> here; which these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> have notoriously done to the utmost of their <hi>Power.</hi> And to say, they were so <hi>Generous</hi> as to have serv'd him <hi>gratis,</hi> is so far from lessening, that it will much ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate the <hi>Crime;</hi> since the Man that betrayes his <hi>Country</hi> for a <hi>Reward,</hi> is far more excusable, than he that does it out of meer <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Ill-will.</hi> I will easily allow them, which I think no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100905:5"/> Man in his <hi>Wits</hi> will deny, that the <hi>French King</hi> has been these many years past, and is like to continue, because 'tis his <hi>Interest,</hi> the great <hi>Disturber</hi> of our <hi>Israels Peace.</hi> He is <hi>sensible,</hi> we are the only <hi>Nation</hi> now able, if united amongst our selves, to give a <hi>Check</hi> to his unlimited <hi>Ambition,</hi> and defeat his long hatch'd Designs of an <hi>Ʋniversal Monarchy.</hi> 'Tis his <hi>Business</hi> therefore to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our <hi>Differences,</hi> and set us together by the <hi>Ears,</hi> till he finds himself in a <hi>Condition</hi> to fall upon us, and destroy us. He has already found out our <hi>Blind Side,</hi> our frightful <hi>Apprehensi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Government</hi> upon every <hi>slight,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no occasion, which the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Book</hi> call'd the <hi>Policy of France,</hi> has long since chalk'd out as the most <hi>infallible way</hi> to break us all to pieces. But if we consider what sort of Men have of late years pursued this very <hi>Method,</hi> with more than <hi>ordinary Zeal,</hi> have studied all ways imaginable to enflame the <hi>Nation,</hi> and bring their <hi>Soveraign</hi> into an <hi>odium</hi> with his <hi>People,</hi> and by this <hi>Means</hi> have given the <hi>French</hi> an <hi>opportunity</hi> to add <hi>Casal</hi> and <hi>Strasbourg, Courtray, Luxemburg,</hi> and other <hi>Places</hi> of <hi>Importance</hi> to his new <hi>Acquisitions,</hi> and to cast several <hi>Slurs</hi> and <hi>Affronts</hi> upon this <hi>Kingdom</hi> both by <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land:</hi> We shall easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find, that whoever receiv'd the <hi>Pensions,</hi> these very <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> that cry so loud against it, were the <hi>grand Promoters</hi> of the <hi>French Interest.</hi> I am sorry this can be said of any, much less of so many of the <hi>Representatives</hi> of the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> or that any should be found among them so unmindful of the <hi>Publick,</hi> or so far infatuated with a <hi>blind unseasonable Zeal</hi> for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as instead of opposing the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> to serve and forward his <hi>Designs.</hi> Yet this much we have to say to our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> that even in that <hi>House there was a Remnant left that bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the knee to Baal,</hi> as <hi>Loyal Subjects,</hi> and as hearty <hi>Lovers</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> as ever sate within those <hi>Walls,</hi> tho' still out-vot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>cunning</hi> and <hi>address</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> who with their plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible <hi>Pretences</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> when they really meant <hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Confusion,</hi> by unhinging the best of <hi>Governments,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all before them. For 'tis plain, there is nothing more <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> to our <hi>present Peace and future Happiness</hi> than the creating such unlucky <hi>divisions and misunderstandings</hi> amongst us; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more necessary for our <hi>Preservation,</hi> than a <hi>lasting union</hi> and a <hi>mutual confidence</hi> between <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People:</hi> And therefore as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100905:5"/> all good <hi>Subjects</hi> are now satisfied, these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> were led by another <hi>Byass</hi> than that of the <hi>Publick good;</hi> so I question not but every true <hi>Englishman</hi> will mark all those for the future, that will run upon the same <hi>Scent,</hi> and look upon them as <hi>Betrayers</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> hir'd by our <hi>Enemies</hi> to prepare us for <hi>Destruction.</hi> But how, I beseech you, cou'd the <hi>Proroguing</hi> of that <hi>Parliament,</hi> be a <hi>promoting</hi> of <hi>French designs?</hi> What have they done, all the while they sate, in opposition to <hi>France,</hi> or what have they omitted to please that <hi>ambitious Prince,</hi> and secure him in his <hi>Conquests;</hi> all their <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Resolutions,</hi> their <hi>Addresses</hi> and <hi>Remonstrances</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all along subservient to his <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Purposes?</hi> The reason was, I suppose, that having set up for <hi>Popular Patriots,</hi> to please the unthinking <hi>Multitude</hi> in some measure, they thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to give them a few <hi>Sugar Plums,</hi> by seeming to huff against the <hi>French,</hi> tho' it was the least of their Thoughts to disoblige so good a <hi>Friend:</hi> As on the other side they pass'd in the following <hi>vote</hi> high <hi>Complements</hi> on their <hi>zealous Sticklers</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> who had bin all along very useful to the <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> to engage them further in the <hi>Cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, that the thanks of this House be given to the City of</hi> London, <hi>for their manifest Loyalty to the King, their care, charge, and vigilancy for the preservation of his Majesties Person, and of the Protestant Religion.</hi> Votes ib.</p>
            <p>I wish the <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> since their <hi>Hand</hi> was in, had so far oblig'd their <hi>Friends</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> as to have given us any one <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> either of their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> or of their <hi>Care</hi> for the <hi>establish'd Religion,</hi> in the whole <hi>course</hi> of their <hi>unhappy Government.</hi> I know very well, there were at that time many <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious Protestants</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> whose prudent <hi>conduct</hi> and <hi>manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Affairs,</hi> has since very much contributed to the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of the <hi>Nation.</hi> But at this time they were only <hi>Cyphers,</hi> out of all <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Command,</hi> and daily run down under the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Tories</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>Masquerade.</hi> As for those <hi>Worthies</hi> here caress'd and applauded for the <hi>Watchmen</hi> of <hi>Israel,</hi> who have since either fled for their <hi>Villanies,</hi> or got under the <hi>Hatches</hi> for several <hi>Misdemeanors,</hi> none but such <hi>Patriots</hi> wou'd have left them unpunish'd, much less have <hi>thank'd</hi> them for their black
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100905:6"/>
               <hi>Exploits;</hi> who made <hi>London</hi> then the <hi>Nursery</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly it was the <hi>Seminary</hi> of the late horrid <hi>Rebellion:</hi> where all the wicked <hi>Measures,</hi> all the <hi>illegal Votes</hi> and <hi>unmannerly Addresses,</hi> that have bin since made use of within <hi>Doors</hi> or without, were contriv'd and hammer'd by <hi>Factious Clubs</hi> and <hi>Cabals,</hi> several Months before the <hi>Parliament</hi> sate, and divers <hi>Copies</hi> distributed among the <hi>Leading men;</hi> whereof the late <hi>King</hi> had a full account given him by a <hi>Gentleman</hi> that seem'd to be of the <hi>Gang,</hi> but was so honest as to let his <hi>Majesty</hi> know the whole <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> In fine, so <hi>Insolent</hi> they were, and so <hi>Violent</hi> against the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> that it was impossible for the <hi>King</hi> to be at ease, or the <hi>Nation</hi> at quiet, while such <hi>Incendiaries</hi> without, to back the <hi>Associators</hi> within <hi>Doors,</hi> had the <hi>management</hi> of the <hi>Capital City,</hi> which in effect is the <hi>Rudder</hi> of the whole <hi>Kingdom;</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all his <hi>Majesties</hi> other endeavours to get the better of the <hi>Faction,</hi> as his now Proroguing, then dissolving his <hi>Parliaments,</hi> (whereby instead of <hi>mending</hi> they became still more <hi>furious</hi> at their next Meeting) signified no more than <hi>Hercules</hi> in the <hi>Fable</hi> now and then cutting off one of <hi>Hydra</hi>'s Heads, which grew <hi>double</hi> as often as cut off. But when the <hi>King,</hi> having tryed in vain all other <hi>Expedients,</hi> seiz'd upon the <hi>Charter</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> which they had forfeited over and over; then, and not till then, he gain'd a compleat Victory, and with that <hi>single blow</hi> cut off all the heads of the <hi>Monster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Associators</hi> finding the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> in <hi>London</hi> so active and so <hi>zealous</hi> in the <hi>Cause,</hi> 'twas no wonder if in <hi>return</hi> they made bold a little to stretch both the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Gospel,</hi> to oblige such useful and necessary <hi>Tools;</hi> especially when they cou'd ease their <hi>Friends,</hi> and run down their <hi>Enemies</hi> with the same <hi>Breath:</hi> And therefore 'tis wisely</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, that it is the Opinion of this House, that the City of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>was burnt in the year</hi> 1666 <hi>by the Papists, designing thereby to introduce Arbitrary Power and Popery into this Kingdom. Votes</hi> 10. Jan. 1680.</p>
            <p>For it was well known, the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> were shrewdly suspected of this horrid <hi>Crime,</hi> six of them having confess'd the <hi>Design</hi> at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100905:6"/> the place of <hi>Execution,</hi> and nam'd the time within a day, near up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on five Months before it happen'd; as may be seen in the <hi>Gazette</hi> 26. of <hi>April</hi> 66. <hi>Nero</hi>'s <hi>Policy</hi> therefore must be us'd, to turn it another way, and the <hi>Wicked</hi> suffer for the Sins of the <hi>Godly;</hi> tho' not out of any hatred either to the worst <hi>Principles</hi> or <hi>Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that ever the <hi>Papists</hi> were accus'd of, but meerly to make them a <hi>Stalking-Horse,</hi> the better to come at their own <hi>Game.</hi> The <hi>Gentlemen</hi> certainly were true <hi>Friends</hi> indeed, who to hide the <hi>Knavery</hi> of their <hi>Party,</hi> generously ventur'd to expose their own <hi>Folly</hi> to the <hi>World.</hi> What <hi>rational connection,</hi> I pray, can we find between the <hi>burning</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and the <hi>introducing</hi> of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or between that and <hi>Arbitrary Power?</hi> As if the <hi>Papists</hi> made <hi>Slavery</hi> a piece of their <hi>Religion,</hi> to whose <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> as <hi>Freeborn Englishmen,</hi> we owe all our <hi>Fundamental Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and even the most excellent <hi>Constitution of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments.</hi> Yet suppose, the <hi>Papists</hi> were such Fools, (as certainly they must be the meerest <hi>Ideots</hi> upon Earth, or they are basely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed) as to prefer <hi>Slavery</hi> to <hi>Liberty,</hi> and think that horrid <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration</hi> serviceable to their <hi>purpose;</hi> how came they to miss of the <hi>End,</hi> at least not to push for't, since they sped so well, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all <hi>Expectation,</hi> in the <hi>Means</hi> they propos'd? Where lay their <hi>Money</hi> in <hi>Bank,</hi> or their <hi>Men</hi> in readiness? Who oppos'd this formidable <hi>Army,</hi> or how came they to vanish without doing some <hi>Execution.?</hi> But enough of this <hi>ridiculous, Nonsensical Stuff,</hi> contriv'd by <hi>Knaves,</hi> and believ'd by <hi>Fools,</hi> and most unluckily <hi>Canoniz'd</hi> at last in St. <hi>Stephens Chappel,</hi> to the everlasting <hi>Shame</hi> of the <hi>Authors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for their intended <hi>kindness</hi> to the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>M.</hi> which really turn'd to his <hi>Disadvantage,</hi> to have such <hi>Mediators</hi> as wanted <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators</hi> and <hi>Pardons</hi> for themselves, to get him restor'd to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Imployments,</hi> it was grounded upon the same <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> with the former. They wheedled the <hi>Poor Man,</hi> to serve their own <hi>Ends,</hi> from his <hi>Duty</hi> and all worldly <hi>Happiness,</hi> with the <hi>Chimerical Hopes</hi> of a <hi>Crown,</hi> which he had neither <hi>Right</hi> to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, nor <hi>Brains</hi> to Support; and being in <hi>Law</hi> but <hi>Filius Populi,</hi> they made him <hi>Don Populario</hi> to his Ruine. For 'tis alwaies ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, that the <hi>Devil owes the Fool a spite, when he makes him a Politician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus our <hi>Associators,</hi> like the <hi>Old Dragon</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100905:7"/> having great Wrath, because they knew they had but a short time,</hi> labour'd to make the best of it they cou'd for their <hi>Purpose;</hi> and therefore ceas'd not to spit their <hi>Venom</hi> on all sides to oblige their <hi>Friends,</hi> and revenge themselves on their <hi>Enemies:</hi> For tho' they expected every <hi>moment</hi> the pale <hi>Messenger</hi> of <hi>Death;</hi> yet like true <hi>Cargilites</hi> they continued to the very last minute <hi>blaspheming</hi> against the <hi>Government.</hi> But the <hi>Fatal</hi> Hour is come at length, and the <hi>Hoggen Moggen,</hi> who acted as if they had the same <hi>Commission</hi> with the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.10.</note> whom God <hi>had set over Nations, and over Kingdoms, to root-out and to pull down, and to spoil and to destroy, and to build, and to plant;</hi> nevertheless with the least <hi>Blast</hi> of their <hi>Princes</hi> breath, they presently gave up the <hi>Ghost,</hi> and moulder'd away into nothing.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>King,</hi> whom no <hi>Irregularities</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> cou'd put out of Love with so good and wholsome a <hi>Constitution,</hi> and the necessities of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> then requiring it, to quiet, if <hi>possible,</hi> the Minds of the <hi>distracted People,</hi> upon the <hi>Dissolution</hi> of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, issued out new <hi>Summons</hi> for calling <hi>another:</hi> Yet consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that for some years before, the <hi>Faction</hi> in the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and their <hi>Agents</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> went hand in hand, support<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and encouraging each other, to the great <hi>prejudice</hi> of the <hi>Publick,</hi> he resolv'd for once to try their <hi>Humor</hi> at <hi>Oxford;</hi> where notwithstanding all the <hi>Endeavours</hi> of the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> while they rul'd the <hi>Roast</hi> in that Ancient and Famous <hi>Nursery</hi> of <hi>Learning,</hi> during the late <hi>Ʋsurpation,</hi> to corrupt the young <hi>Collegians</hi> with the old <hi>Leaven, Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> were still triumphant.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Faction</hi> quickly apprehending the <hi>Disadvantages</hi> they shou'd lie under, near so <hi>Learned,</hi> and so <hi>Loyal</hi> an <hi>Ʋniversity,</hi> where their <hi>Shams</hi> wou'd not take, nor their <hi>Practices</hi> bear <hi>Water;</hi> where they shou'd want their <hi>Cabals</hi> to prepare <hi>Schemes,</hi> and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly <hi>Rabble</hi> to make a <hi>Noise,</hi> immediately put their Heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to divert this, as to them, most <hi>Fatal Resolution.</hi> And having drawn up an <hi>Ʋnmannerly</hi> sort of a <hi>Petition,</hi> not so much <hi>Praying</hi> as <hi>Threatning</hi> the <hi>King</hi> with the ill Consequences of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving his <hi>Parliament</hi> from <hi>London;</hi> which they got sign'd by as many <hi>Lords</hi> as they cou'd get of their <hi>Gang,</hi> to the number of <hi>Sixteen,</hi> they pitch'd upon the unhappy <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Essex</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent it to his <hi>Majesty;</hi> who chearfully undertook the <hi>Province,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100905:7"/> that he might seem the <hi>Ringleader</hi> of the <hi>Party,</hi> and usher'd it in with a most <hi>Impertinent Harangue</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">25. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1680.</note> which they had <hi>prepar'd</hi> for him upon that <hi>Occasion.</hi> But the <hi>King</hi> was too <hi>Wise</hi> to be impos'd upon by such Men; whom he knew so well, that their <hi>Petition,</hi> in stead of working any <hi>Change,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd him in his former <hi>Purpose;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Petitioners</hi> were dismiss'd without any further <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This unexpected <hi>Repulse</hi> put the <hi>Faction</hi> to some <hi>Stand;</hi> yet having no other <hi>Remedy,</hi> they got the <hi>Speech</hi> and <hi>Petition</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly printed, by way of <hi>Appeal,</hi> as their <hi>Custom</hi> was, to the <hi>Multitude;</hi> but in few days after, the chief <hi>Heads</hi> of both were briefly confuted by an honest <hi>Gentleman,</hi> whose <hi>Answer,</hi> you tell me, never came to your hands; and therefore because <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Short,</hi> and withal somewhat <hi>Prophetical,</hi> as to that unfortunate <hi>Earl,</hi> I will here insert for your <hi>Perusal.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THo' the great <hi>Esteem</hi> I have always had as well for your <hi>Lordships Parts</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> as your <hi>Fathers Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty,</hi> inclines me to make a favourable Construction of your <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Actions;</hi> yet the late <hi>Speech,</hi> and <hi>Petition</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish'd under your <hi>Name,</hi> are of so strange a nature, and of so ill an aspect in our present <hi>Circumstances,</hi> that I cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with my <hi>Thoughts</hi> upon that unseasonable <hi>Subject;</hi> wherein did I not see my <hi>Soveraign</hi> so nearly concern'd, that many do construe, this was not so much <hi>Petitioning,</hi> as <hi>Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> his <hi>Sacred Majesty,</hi> I wou'd have silently pass'd it over, and buried my <hi>Resentments</hi> in Oblivion.</p>
                  <p>I am sorry, <hi>my Lord,</hi> you begin with so weak an <hi>Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> from <hi>Histories</hi> and <hi>Records,</hi> as that many <hi>Parliaments</hi> have been unfortunate when call'd at Places remote from the <hi>Capital City.</hi> Did you ever observe how unfortunate many have been, when call'd in this <hi>Capital City;</hi> or how many have been unfortunate, when elsewhere conven'd? Do not all <hi>Writers</hi> of the <hi>late Rebellion</hi> observe it a great <hi>oversight</hi> in our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> not to have call'd his long <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>York,</hi> or some other Place, remote from <hi>London;</hi> where so many <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cabals</hi> were constantly held, and so many Pernicious <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances</hi> daily hammer'd, besides the <hi>Rabbles tumultuous</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100905:8"/> to <hi>Westminster-Hall,</hi> and the <hi>Common Councils</hi> petitioning, or rather advising his <hi>Majesty, (Mechanicks</hi> turning <hi>Politicians,</hi> and leaving their <hi>Shops</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> to sit at the <hi>Helm</hi> of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment)</hi> that all wise men conclude, thence came the <hi>Plague</hi> of <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Desolation</hi> upon the whole <hi>Kingdom?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But your <hi>Observation</hi> is not so <hi>weak,</hi> as your <hi>Presidents</hi> are <hi>Emphatical</hi> and <hi>Mysterious.</hi> You instance three unhappy <hi>Kings,</hi> and without the least <hi>ground</hi> in <hi>History,</hi> you seem to suppose the Places of calling their <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the Cause of their <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages.</hi> I am sure, <hi>my Lord,</hi> you know the contrary is manifest by our most Authentick <hi>Monuments</hi> and <hi>Records.</hi> To <hi>Popular Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealousies,</hi> fomented by <hi>Ambitious</hi> and <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented Grandees</hi> and <hi>pretended Patriots,</hi> these, as most <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> ow'd all their troubles and calamities; as now we do in a great <hi>Proportion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To these <hi>Henry</hi> II. by you mention'd, ow'd the <hi>unnatural Broils</hi> and <hi>Distractions</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> when they and <hi>Lewis</hi> the VII. <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> to make the Case the more <hi>Parallel,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the <hi>Son</hi> to rebell against the <hi>Father;</hi> in which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless they were thus far more <hi>excusable</hi> than <hi>others,</hi> that the <hi>Son</hi> was no <hi>Bastard,</hi> but the undoubted <hi>Heir</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> and a <hi>titular King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>These were in like manner the chief Cause of all the <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs</hi> and <hi>Miseryes</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Third</hi>'s <hi>Reign,</hi> when under the Colour of redressing the <hi>Peoples Grievances,</hi> they brought upon the <hi>Nation</hi> the greatest <hi>Grievance</hi> of all, an Intestine <hi>Civil War</hi> for many years together: And tho' they loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretended to fight for the Liberty of the <hi>Subject,</hi> yet themselves were no better than so many <hi>Tyrants;</hi> as anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and modern <hi>Authors</hi> have observ'd. <hi>Baker</hi> p. 86.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>Henry</hi> VI. his <hi>Fate</hi> was the <hi>Consequence</hi> of his <hi>Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers Ʋsurpation;</hi> for <hi>De male quaesitis vix gaudet tertius Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> The People at last weary of their <hi>Change,</hi> began to open their <hi>Eyes,</hi> and think it better to submit to their <hi>Lawful Prince,</hi> than to a <hi>violent Ʋsurper.</hi> Nevertheless this Revolution cou'd not have been effected but with a great deal of difficulty, had not a gap been open'd by the <hi>Ambition</hi> of wicked <hi>States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who to have the sole <hi>Management</hi> of <hi>Affairs</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, contriv'd the death of the <hi>Kings Ʋncle,</hi> and only <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100905:8"/> the <hi>Good Duke</hi> of <hi>Gloucester;</hi> as now some conspire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>His Royal Highness,</hi> the better to enable themselves to dispose of the <hi>King</hi> as they please.</p>
                  <p>These are the chief <hi>Heads</hi> of your unseasonable <hi>Speech,</hi> but your <hi>Petition</hi> runs a little further. In the first place you aggravate the <hi>Dangers</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> of which all true <hi>Protestants</hi> are sufficiently <hi>Apprehensive;</hi> yet withal, <hi>my Lord,</hi> we are too sensible the <hi>Papists</hi> are not our only <hi>Enemies.</hi> We have whole Swarms of <hi>ungovernable Sectaries,</hi> and <hi>Republicans</hi> in great numbers, that seem to hate the <hi>Name,</hi> but in themselves love the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> that pretend to stand for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but really advance <hi>Presbytery;</hi> Infine, that wou'd fain perswade us they are great <hi>Lovers</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> tho' by their <hi>Actions</hi> we may easily see, they care but little for his <hi>Government.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You are troubl'd it seems, that the next <hi>Parliament</hi> is to meet at <hi>Oxford, where</hi> (you say) <hi>neither Lords nor Commons can be in safety, but will be daily expos'd to the Swords of the Papists, and their Adherents; of whom too many have crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Majesties Guards.</hi> Do you know, <hi>my Lord,</hi> of any such <hi>Papists</hi> now in the <hi>Guards?</hi> If you do, 'tis your Duty to your <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> to have them secur'd: If not, 'tis a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less <hi>Surmise,</hi> and a very frivolous <hi>Pretence,</hi> unfit to be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd by Persons of <hi>Honour.</hi> Certain it is, we have more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to believe such unseasonable <hi>Petitioners</hi> are addicted to <hi>Presbytery,</hi> than his <hi>Majesties Guards</hi> inclin'd to <hi>Popery:</hi> For the later do openly protest against the <hi>Papists,</hi> have often ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Tests</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> against that <hi>Religion;</hi> but the former are <hi>zealous Solicitors</hi> for the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and endeavour to unite them to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> not by their coming to us, but ours to them, we loseing our own <hi>Ground,</hi> and they still keeping theirs. But to wave this, if his <hi>Majesty</hi> thinks himself safe at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and doubts not to commit his <hi>Sacred Person</hi> to his <hi>Guards,</hi> what Reason have you to apprehend any <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi> Sure, 'tis his <hi>Majesties death,</hi> not yours, the <hi>Papists</hi> have hitherto design'd: How then can you be so <hi>Apprehensive,</hi> while he is <hi>secure?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Kings Evidence,</hi> I doubt not but they will chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully endure a little <hi>Inconvenience,</hi> to make an end of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100905:9"/>
                     <hi>Execrable Plot.</hi> 'Tis an advantage most of them have, that they have bin brought up and us'd to <hi>want</hi> and <hi>hardship;</hi> which now, I am confident, they will not decline, to consummate the great <hi>Work</hi> they have so well begun.</p>
                  <p>My Lord, I wish as heartily as any man in <hi>England,</hi> the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Meetings of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and the good <hi>Correspondence</hi> of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People.</hi> I am perhaps as much concern'd as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to have the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> preserv'd inviolable. Yet when I see those, that shou'd be the Preservers of this <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> first invade it, and endeavour to <hi>Monopolize Arbitrary Power</hi> to <hi>themselves,</hi> I think <hi>self-preservation</hi> allows me to oppose them. 'Tis a true saying, <hi>Corruptio optimi pessima,</hi> and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells us, that <hi>Parliaments may err as well as Kings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will Conclude with a short <hi>Reflection</hi> on some Transactions preceding the <hi>long Parliament</hi> in the late <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Reign;</hi> where 'tis observable, that his <hi>Majesty</hi> finding his <hi>Parliaments</hi> still <hi>Retrograde,</hi> and bent rather to foment than compose the <hi>Differences</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in <hi>September</hi> 40. He summon'd the <hi>Great Council</hi> of his <hi>Peers,</hi> to consult about the weighty <hi>Affairs</hi> of the <hi>Nation: But this</hi> (saith a late <hi>Historian) was not very well lik'd of by those who favour'd the Scots, whose chief Design aim'd at the calling of a Parliament, which they fear'd the meeting of the Peers might prevent. Wherefore the Earls of</hi> Bedford, Hertford, Essex, Warwick, Mouldgrave, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingbrook <hi>and</hi> Bristol, <hi>and the Lords</hi> Say, Brook, Paget, Mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, <hi>and the Lord</hi> Edward Howard, <hi>presented a Petition to the King, representing many great Distempers and Dangers, threatning the Church and State, and his Royal Person; as Sundry Innovations in Matters of Religion; increase of Popery, by employing Papists in places of Trust; the great Mischief that might ensue, if the Forces rais'd in</hi> Ireland <hi>shou'd be brought into</hi> England, &amp;c. <hi>For Remedy whereof, they pray, that a Parliament might be Summoned, to redress these Grievances, and punish the Authors; and likewise to compose the War with</hi> Scotland <hi>without Blood, and unite both Kingdoms against the Common Enemy of the Reformed Religion.</hi> And this was seconded by another <hi>Petition</hi> to the same Effect, from their <hi>Common Hackney, the Common Council</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> See Baker p. 470.</p>
                  <p>These, <hi>my Lord,</hi> were as fair <hi>pretences,</hi> and as plausible <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements</hi> to have a <hi>Parliament</hi> then call'd, as any you can offer at present for the Meeting of the next in <hi>London;</hi> and yet the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100905:9"/>
                     <hi>World</hi> knows what pernicious <hi>Designs</hi> were then a <hi>hatching</hi> against the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> by those very <hi>Persons</hi> who promoted that <hi>Petition:</hi> and happy had his Majesty and the whole <hi>Nation</hi> bin, had he rejected their <hi>Importunity. To every thing there is a Season,</hi> saith the <hi>Wise Man;</hi> and without doubt there is a <hi>Season</hi> for <hi>Petitioning.</hi> 'Tis certainly our <hi>Duty,</hi> with all <hi>Humility</hi> to beg of our <hi>Soveraign</hi> what we think <hi>necessary</hi> for the <hi>Publick;</hi> but to press him to it, when he declares against it, for good <hi>Reasons</hi> as we ought in good manners to suppose, is a very great <hi>Presumption,</hi> not to be endur'd in a <hi>Subject.</hi> If the <hi>Laws</hi> have settled in the <hi>King</hi> the absolute <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Calling, Adjourning, Proroguing</hi> and <hi>Dissolving</hi> his <hi>Parliaments,</hi> when and where he pleases, shall we be Wiser than the<note n="*" place="margin">Neminem opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet Sapientiorem es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>se Legibus. <hi>Cook.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Laws,</hi> and Limit our <hi>Princes</hi> Will, or question his <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Fine,</hi> when <hi>Discontented Statesmen</hi> are found the <hi>Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of such <hi>Petitions,</hi> 'tis <hi>Natural</hi> to suspect they do it for some Sinister <hi>Design; Timeo Danaos &amp; dona ferentes.</hi> If the great <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician Achitophel</hi> hang'd himself through discontent, because his <hi>Counsel</hi> was not follow'd, we cannot in <hi>Prudence</hi> but think others will leave no <hi>Stone</hi> unturn'd to gratify their <hi>Passion.</hi> There are some <hi>Weathercocks</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> who had a hand in all the <hi>Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions</hi> of their time, <hi>modo harum, modo illarum partium,</hi> but never <hi>Faithful</hi> to any; if Your <hi>Lordship</hi> be so far overseen, as to joyn with <hi>Those,</hi> they will cetainly leave you in the <hi>Lurch,</hi> when 'tis too <hi>Late</hi> to Repent. Therefore in time consider the <hi>Wise Man</hi>'s Advice: <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and Meddle not with them that are given to Change; for their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity shall rise suddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both.</hi> Prov. 24.21.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>I am Yours</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>28 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1680/1.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now if we compare the last <hi>Paragraph</hi> of this <hi>Letter</hi> with the <hi>Fatal End</hi> of that <hi>unhappy Earl,</hi> we shall find the <hi>Prediction</hi> veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to a Hair, and the <hi>Gentleman's Conjectures</hi> turn'd in a manner into a <hi>Prophecy.</hi> The <hi>Poor Man</hi> found at last to his <hi>Sorrow,</hi> he was left in the <hi>Lurch</hi> by Crooked <hi>Achitophel,</hi> when it was indeed <hi>too late to Repent;</hi> and therefore out of <hi>Remorse</hi> of <hi>Conscience,</hi> and deep <hi>Despair,</hi> for the <hi>baseness</hi> of his <hi>Crimes</hi> against his <hi>Soveraign,</hi> rendred
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100905:10"/> yet more <hi>odious</hi> with the <hi>blackest</hi> of <hi>Ingratitudes,</hi> in conspiring the Death of his <hi>Prince</hi> that heap'd so many favours upon him, and in a great measure rais'd him from <hi>Nothing;</hi> notwithstanding all his <hi>Pretended Zeal</hi> for <hi>Religion,</hi> he was yet so <hi>Irreligious</hi> and <hi>Wicked,</hi> as to lay <hi>violent hands</hi> upon himself.</p>
            <p>But enough of this ungrateful Subject; and now let us observe a little the <hi>Motions</hi> of that <hi>Abortive Parliament</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> whither the <hi>Leading Members</hi> are conducted, as it were in <hi>Triumph,</hi> by Formidable Bodies of the <hi>Faction,</hi> to strike Terror into all their <hi>Opposers.</hi> The many Foils and disappointments they receiv'd in the Preceding <hi>Parliaments,</hi> were so far from bringing them to any <hi>Calmness</hi> or Moderation, that now they are resolv'd with greater <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> than ever, to pursue their former Designs. In the <hi>Westminster Parliament,</hi> tho' they made bold to insert in one of their <hi>Bills</hi> a <hi>Clause</hi> for repealing the <hi>Statutes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Votes</hi> 16 Dec. 1680.</note>
               <hi>de Scandalis Magnatum,</hi> thereby to bring the <hi>Lords</hi> upon an even <hi>Level</hi> with themselves; and to Vote several <hi>Peers,</hi> without any Tryal or Conviction,<note n="*" place="margin">7 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1680.</note>
               <hi>Enemies to the King and Kingdom,</hi> for advising his <hi>Majesty</hi> against the <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Exclusion:</hi> Yet they were so <hi>modest,</hi> as not to declare against the whole <hi>House,</hi> notwithstanding that his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> had told them in his <hi>Message</hi> some daies before,<note n="*" place="margin">4 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1680.</note>
               <hi>He was confirm'd in his Opinion against the Bill of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion by the Judgment of the House of Lords, who rejected it.</hi> But here we find them of a <hi>Braver Spirit, fit to bind Kings in Chains, and Nobles in Fetters of Iron:</hi> And therefore when the <hi>Lords,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the known <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> rejected their contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>impeaching Fitzharris,</hi> and referr'd him to be Tryed at <hi>Common Law,</hi> they like <hi>bold Brittons,</hi> charg'd the <hi>whole House</hi> of <hi>Peers</hi> with the highest <hi>Violation</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi> imaginable: And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, That it is the undoubted Right of the Commons in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament assembled, to impeach before the Lords any Peer or Commoner for Treason, or any other Crime or Misdeanour. And that the refusal of the Lords to proceed in Parliament upon such Impeachment, is a denial of Justice, and a violation of the Constitution of Parliaments. Votes</hi> 26 March 1681.</p>
            <p>But I wish the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> had bin so just to themselves, as to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100905:10"/> have told us, What <hi>Grounds</hi> they proceeded upon in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, in Case they had any, besides their <hi>unaccountable Nemine Contradicente.</hi> I am sure, if we understand the <hi>great Charter</hi> of our <hi>Liberties,</hi> and the <hi>Fundamental Birthright</hi> of every <hi>Commoner,</hi> to be Tryed by <hi>Juries</hi> in all <hi>Capital Crimes,</hi> where the <hi>Criminal</hi> is allow'd to make divers <hi>Peremptory Challenges,</hi> and as many more as he can shew <hi>Cause,</hi> 'tis most undoubted, nothing cou'd have been more <hi>Illegal</hi> than the <hi>Impeachment</hi> of <hi>Fitzharris,</hi> nothing more <hi>unwarrantable</hi> than this very <hi>Resolve.</hi> Besides 'tis well known, that in the 4th Year of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. after the <hi>Lords</hi> had been prevail'd upon to give <hi>Judgment</hi> on Sir <hi>Simon de Bereford</hi> and several other <hi>Commoners,</hi> for the <hi>Murder</hi> of <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. and his <hi>Brother</hi> the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> there is an express <hi>Proviso</hi> still extant upon <hi>Record,</hi> that the <hi>Lords</hi> shou'd not for the future be oblig'd to judge any but their <hi>Peers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And it is assented and accorded by our Lord the King, and all the Grandees in full Parliament; that albeit the Peers, as Judges of the Parliament, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve taken upon them, and rendred Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That yet the said <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers, who n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w are, or shall be in time to come, be not bound or charged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> render Judgments upon others than their Peers. Nor that the Peers of the Land have POWER to do this, but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ever to be discharged and acquitted: And that the aforesaid Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment rendred be not drawn to Example or Consequence in time to come, whereby the said</hi> Peers shall do contrary to the Laws of the Land, <hi>if the like case happen, which God forbid.</hi> 4 Ed. 3. N. 6. <hi>And pursu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to this Proviso, when Sir</hi> William Cogan <hi>was accus'd in</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>by Sir</hi> Richard Clevedon, 5. R. 2. <hi>N.</hi> 43 and 44. <hi>the</hi> Lords <hi>having heard the</hi> Cause, <hi>remitted both</hi> Parties <hi>to the</hi> Common-Law.</p>
            <p>Where then is the <hi>undoubted Right</hi> of the <hi>Commons</hi> to impeach, or what <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Statute</hi> can <hi>warrant</hi> their imposing upon the <hi>Lords</hi> to judge whom they please, contrary to such express <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament?</hi> Or what cou'd be their <hi>Reason</hi> to be so much concern'd for <hi>Fitzharris,</hi> a <hi>profess'd Papist,</hi> but to delay his Trial, when after <hi>Impeachment</hi> he cou'd not be brought to <hi>Justice</hi> but at their Suit, that by assuring him his <hi>Life,</hi> they might force him to pretend some new <hi>Discoveries,</hi> to breed more <hi>Confusion?</hi> They knew very well the Man had nothing to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100905:11"/> but his own <hi>Villanous Inventions,</hi> which he purposely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd to save his Neck from the <hi>Gallows,</hi> charging himself with new <hi>Crimes,</hi> to avoid the punishment of the old. And Sir <hi>R. C.</hi> one of his Godfathers in <hi>Newgate</hi> made it plain enough, when he told the <hi>House</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Debates. p. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Fitzharris</hi> ask'd him, <hi>whether he had not said enough to save his Life?</hi> But still it was the same thing to them, <hi>Plots true or false</hi> wou'd equally serve their turn; or rather false ones wou'd be more <hi>Ʋseful,</hi> because they cou'd turn them which way they pleas'd: And therefore to the very last they us'd all their <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours</hi> to bring him off, <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Wrong,</hi> and to frighten the <hi>Judges</hi> from their <hi>Duty,</hi> they pass'd the following <hi>Vote;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, that for any Inferiour Court to proceed against</hi> Edward Fitzharris, <hi>or any other Person lying under an Impeachment in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for the same crimes for which he or they stand Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is an high breach of the priviledge of Parliament. Votes</hi> 26. <hi>March</hi> 81.</p>
            <p>Sure these <hi>Gentlemen</hi> dreamt they were gone back to 41. and made <hi>perpetual Dictators,</hi> that they offer'd at this Rate to impose their wild <hi>Ordinances</hi> upon the <hi>Nation,</hi> in opposition to the <hi>fundamental Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi> 'Tis pity his <hi>Majesty</hi> did not suffer them to sit a little longer, that we might have more of such <hi>edifying Resolutions.</hi> And I wonder how cou'd <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People</hi> be weary of so <hi>obliging</hi> a <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd with a great deal of <hi>Pains</hi> and <hi>Industry,</hi> to imitate <hi>Christ's</hi> saying in the <hi>Revelation, Behold I make all things new,</hi> Rev. 21.5. <hi>New Laws, new Religions,</hi> and many <hi>new</hi> frames of <hi>Government,</hi> might we be assur'd of by this time, had not the <hi>Almighty</hi> seen their <hi>Predecessors,</hi> the <hi>Rebellious Long-Parliament,</hi> had given us too much of those <hi>Blessings.</hi> If <hi>Caligula</hi> suck'd blood when a <hi>Child,</hi> what cou'd <hi>People</hi> hope from him when a <hi>Man?</hi> And if the <hi>Faction</hi> at <hi>Oxford</hi> arriv'd in six <hi>days</hi> time to that <hi>height</hi> of <hi>Insolence,</hi> as the <hi>Commons</hi> in 41. did not come near in six <hi>months,</hi> what a happy <hi>Reformation</hi> might we expect, had they also been made <hi>perpetual.</hi> But they liv'd too fast to live long, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding this <hi>extravagant Vote,</hi> with the terrible <hi>Bugbear</hi> in the Belly on't, the <hi>priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> which had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100905:11"/> sunk both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Gospel, Fitzharris</hi> was brought to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> and discover'd at the place of <hi>Execution</hi> both his <hi>Own</hi> and his <hi>Patrons</hi> villany.</p>
            <p>'Tis observable that in K. <hi>James</hi> 1. his time the <hi>bloody Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> concern'd in the <hi>Gun-powder Treason,</hi> were all tryed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed by the course of the <hi>Common Law;</hi> and tho' the <hi>Parliament</hi> was then sitting, and the <hi>Design</hi> level'd as much against them, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Royal Family,</hi> yet not one of them did the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> offer to impeach; neither is it to be imagin'd, that so wise a <hi>Prince,</hi> and so great a <hi>Master</hi> of <hi>Kings-craft,</hi> wou'd have suffer'd them to meddle with any of his <hi>Prisoners,</hi> since he did not allow them to take the least <hi>cognizance</hi> of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where the <hi>Inferiour Courts</hi> had <hi>power</hi> to proceed. No <hi>vot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Plots</hi> was then in fashion, no <hi>examining</hi> of <hi>Witnesses</hi> by <hi>Secret Committees</hi> of the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> no suing of <hi>Pardons</hi> or <hi>Rewards</hi> for mercenary needy <hi>Informers,</hi> as we have had of late days, to carry on the most uncouth ill-shap'd <hi>Monster,</hi> that ever appear'd in <hi>Nature.</hi> All was calmly examin'd, and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially determin'd in the ordinary <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Justice</hi> without any further <hi>Appeal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And many are of <hi>Opinion,</hi> it wou'd have been very much for the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Wellfare</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> had the late <hi>King</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the like <hi>method</hi> in the <hi>prosecution</hi> of <hi>Oates</hi> his <hi>Popish</hi> Plot, which wou'd have prevented the <hi>distractions</hi> of his <hi>People,</hi> and wholly defeated the <hi>designs</hi> of his <hi>Enemies;</hi> who no sooner got the <hi>management</hi> of that <hi>ridiculous Stuff</hi> into their hands, but they improv'd it every day more and more to his <hi>Majesties</hi> disadvantage, still grafting <hi>new Plots</hi> on the <hi>old Stock,</hi> to keep the <hi>People</hi> in a <hi>continual ferment,</hi> till the <hi>grand Plot</hi> appear'd at last, which had not <hi>Providence</hi> miraculuosly prevented, wou'd have certainly prov'd the <hi>Ruine</hi> both of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi> And who, I pray, were the <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of this horrid <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> but the great <hi>Dictators</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> and the noisy <hi>Assertors</hi> of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> in those two <hi>Parliaments?</hi> where, as we are since convinc'd, our true <hi>Protestant Patriots</hi> made all this bustle about the <hi>Popish Plot</hi> for no other end, but that they might un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Ʋmbrage</hi> of that, carry on their <hi>own undiscover'd.</hi> Well might they cry his <hi>Majesties Life</hi> was still in <hi>Danger,</hi> who best knew what <hi>Hellish Machinations</hi> they had on foot against his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100905:12"/>
               <hi>Sacred Person,</hi> which yet they labour'd with a great deal of Art and Cunning to throw upon the <hi>Papists,</hi> on whom they had already voted<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Votes</hi> 2. <hi>Nov.</hi> 80.</note>
               <hi>in case the King shou'd come by any violent Death, they wou'd revenge it to the utmost,</hi> tho' none more likely to act it than some of themselves, as soon afterwards appear'd. For, when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that neither their <hi>illegal Votes,</hi> nor <hi>insolent Addresses,</hi> nor all their other <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Contrivances</hi> cou'd prevail with the <hi>King</hi> to lay his <hi>Crown</hi> at their feet; and found moreover, that the main <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> their <hi>Friends</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> whose <hi>Purses</hi> and <hi>Consciences</hi> they always had at their <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> were upon declining, and like to loose the <hi>Charter</hi> they had so vigorously made use of against the <hi>Giver:</hi> then they thought it <hi>high time</hi> to bestir themselves, and try since no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else was like to succeed, what cou'd <hi>Sword</hi> and <hi>Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbuss</hi> do.</p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Plot</hi> indeed, and the well-contriv'd <hi>Design,</hi> where no <hi>Art</hi> was wanting to secure the success, no <hi>Power</hi> but <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> able to defeat it. The <hi>Common People</hi> were already mannag'd to some purpose, the <hi>Knaves</hi> prepar'd for executing any Villany, and the <hi>well-meaning Fools</hi> kept still gaping af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>ridiculous Contrivances</hi> of the <hi>Papists,</hi> which if compar'd to this, will seem but a meer <hi>Phantome</hi> or <hi>Shadow:</hi> For their forty Thousand <hi>Black Bills,</hi> their <hi>Screw'd Guns</hi> and <hi>Silver Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets,</hi> their <hi>Spanish Pilgrims</hi> and <hi>Irish Auxiliaries,</hi> their <hi>White-Horse Consult</hi> and <hi>D' Oliva</hi>'s <hi>Commissions,</hi> and <hi>in fine,</hi> the whole frame of that <hi>Bears Cub,</hi> is no more than a <hi>Childish piece</hi> of <hi>Pageantry,</hi> in comparison of the late <hi>Conspirators</hi> methodical <hi>Attacques</hi> upon the <hi>Government;</hi> as their <hi>seditious Petitions</hi> and <hi>factious Addresses,</hi> their <hi>riotous Elections</hi> and <hi>perjur'd Ignoramus's</hi> their <hi>Anti-Monarchical Bill</hi> of <hi>Exclusion</hi> and <hi>treasonable Project</hi> of <hi>Association,</hi> and to crown the Work, their <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Six</hi> and <hi>Rye-house undertaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Train</hi> is so <hi>Obvious</hi> and <hi>Visible</hi> in the <hi>Later,</hi> and the <hi>Chain</hi> so easie to be trac'd <hi>link</hi> by <hi>link,</hi> while there is but little or no <hi>Coherence</hi> in the <hi>Former,</hi> that the most any man in his right <hi>Wits</hi> can do, is to believe any <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> or <hi>disbelieve</hi> the least <hi>tittle</hi> of the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why shou'd I seek <hi>knots</hi> in <hi>Bulrushes,</hi> or dwell any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100905:12"/> on a thing so plain? the whole <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> is suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently reveal'd, and not only sworn to by many of the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> but own'd and confess'd by the <hi>dying Conspirators;</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we have little or nothing to support the Credit of the <hi>other,</hi> but the bare <hi>oaths</hi> of a <hi>pack</hi> of <hi>Jayl-birds</hi> and the most noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious of <hi>Villains,</hi> who for their <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> were ready to swear any thing, while they had a head-strong <hi>Faction</hi> to back them, and pawm upon the <hi>People</hi> their <hi>Romantick Dreams</hi> for <hi>new Revelations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if at last we sum up our <hi>Accounts,</hi> and compute our <hi>Loss</hi> and <hi>Gain</hi> upon the whole matter, as every <hi>prudent Man</hi> will do even in his private <hi>Concerns,</hi> what is the <hi>Nation</hi> the better for this way of proceeding? The <hi>Monarchy</hi> was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not only brought low, but upon the very brink of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction;</hi> the <hi>establish'd Religion</hi> defam'd, and the <hi>Orthodox Clergy</hi> made a <hi>Grievance;</hi> divers of his <hi>Majesties</hi> good <hi>Subjects</hi> daily harrass'd, and toss'd from <hi>Post</hi> to <hi>Pillar;</hi> our <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> lost abroad; and our <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Commerce</hi> in a manner ruin'd: And all this while not one to be nam'd, that was a <hi>Gainer</hi> by the matter, but <hi>scandalous Libellers, factious Newsmong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and <hi>perjur'd Informers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is not all, our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> which in former Ages were deservedly look'd upon as the great <hi>Physitians</hi> of the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> (because of late years the <hi>Leading</hi> Members in the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> prov'd such <hi>Quacks</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> as seem'd to have only the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Killing,</hi> but not of <hi>Curing</hi> any) suffer'd so much in their <hi>Credit,</hi> especially with such as are apt to throw the <hi>Faults</hi> of the <hi>Professors</hi> upon the <hi>Profession,</hi> and the <hi>Miscarriages</hi> of some <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> upon the whole <hi>Constitution,</hi> that many are of <hi>Opinion,</hi> it will be no small <hi>difficulty</hi> for the next to <hi>Retrieve</hi> their <hi>Reputation.</hi> It grieves me to find what some <hi>Ingenious</hi> Gentlemen have observ'd, that of the eight, which have been summon'd these 60 years past, we have had but <hi>One</hi> that we cou'd truly call a <hi>Loyal</hi> or <hi>good Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The rest, through the <hi>unhappy Choice</hi> of ill <hi>Members,</hi> who aim'd more at their own <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Designs</hi> than the <hi>Publick good,</hi> some endeavouring by <hi>Caballing</hi> and <hi>Bawling</hi> against the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to get themselves bought off with <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> others labouring to promote <hi>Fanaticism</hi> and turn the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> into a <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> have occasion'd such <hi>distractions,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100905:13"/> such wild <hi>Notions</hi> and <hi>Chimaera</hi>'s among the <hi>People,</hi> that many an honest man thinks he has <hi>Reason</hi> to wish, as the <hi>least of the two Evils,</hi> rather to have no <hi>Parliaments,</hi> than to be plagued with the like for the future.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Distemper,</hi> I hope, is now pretty well over, and the <hi>Nation</hi> having had sufficient <hi>Experience</hi> of the <hi>Fatal</hi> consequences of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> will (I doubt not) take such <hi>Measures</hi> at this time, as will make the next a <hi>healing, restoring Parliament;</hi> such as will not increase, but rather redress our Grievances, bring all the <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> to Condign <hi>Punishment,</hi> procure and fix a good understanding between <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and thereby (the only <hi>Means</hi> to do it) <hi>Retrieve</hi> the <hi>Reputation</hi> their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors</hi> have so unluckily lost, to the great <hi>Prejudice</hi> of the <hi>Publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>sure</hi> and <hi>short way</hi> to our <hi>present Settlement</hi> and future Happiness, so earnestly wish'd for by all <hi>Loyal Subjects,</hi> and no less dreaded by the <hi>Disturbers</hi> of our <hi>Israels Peace;</hi> who have therefore now all their <hi>Engines</hi> at work, to render this as fruitless as they have former <hi>Parliaments.</hi> The <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and the <hi>Republicans,</hi> of late turn'd <hi>Trimmers,</hi> as the more <hi>Mischievous</hi> sort of <hi>Animals,</hi> and such as fancy themselves <hi>disoblig'd,</hi> or whose Crimes have render'd them <hi>obnoxious</hi> to the <hi>Government,</hi> who think they can have no <hi>Safety,</hi> at least no <hi>possibility</hi> of compassing their <hi>Ends,</hi> but by our <hi>disorder</hi> and <hi>Confusion,</hi> now keep constant <hi>Clubs</hi> and <hi>Cabals,</hi> in all the <hi>Corners</hi> of the <hi>Town,</hi> to contrive such <hi>Schemes</hi> and <hi>Measures,</hi> as they think most proper to frustrate all honest Mens <hi>Expectations,</hi> by rendring the next Sessions ineffectual.</p>
            <p>It has been always their <hi>Policy</hi> to begin with <hi>Religion,</hi> as the most <hi>popular Topick</hi> they can make use of, to engage the <hi>unthinking Multitude</hi> in the Cause, according to <hi>Machiavel</hi>'s Rule, <hi>Quoties vis fallere plebem, finge Deum:</hi> Tho' 'tis well known, the old <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philosophers</hi> were far better <hi>Christians</hi> than such <hi>noisy Reformers</hi> as we have had of late days, who were every <hi>Moon</hi> for <hi>chopping</hi> and <hi>changing, paring</hi> and <hi>clipping Religion,</hi> till they wou'd have left us none at all. It was <hi>Erasmus</hi> his <hi>Drollery, Quid rerum nunc geri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Anglia? Consulitur de Religione.</hi> And it has been our <hi>Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> ever since to have been perplex'd with the same <hi>Endless Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultations;</hi> till at length <hi>Christianity</hi> it self was Spirited away from among us by an <hi>Ignis Fatuus</hi> of an <hi>Imaginary Religion,</hi> and nothing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100905:13"/> in a manner left to the <hi>Establish'd Church,</hi> that we cou'd call <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> but <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Persecution.</hi> And all this while, which was our <hi>fatal Error,</hi> we never consider'd before-hand the <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>moral Actions</hi> of those <hi>Refiners</hi> of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that we might thereby <hi>know what spirit they were of:</hi> But, as if <hi>God</hi> wanted the <hi>Devils</hi> assistance to defend his <hi>Church,</hi> the loosest <hi>Debauchees,</hi> and the greatest <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> no sooner pretended to stand up for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> but they were immediately Canoniz'd by the <hi>gaping Crowd</hi> into <hi>tutelar Saints</hi> and <hi>true Protestant Patriots.</hi> Thus poor <hi>Perkin Warbeck,</hi> and his good natur'd <hi>Cornudo,</hi> to omit many <hi>hundreds</hi> more of the same <hi>Stamp,</hi> were cryed up for the <hi>main Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> that stood in the <hi>Gap</hi> against the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undations</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> tho' at the same time little better than <hi>Atheists,</hi> and when their <hi>Vizards</hi> were pull'd off, and they cou'd stay no longer here, then each of them thought fit, for their <hi>Spiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, to lead about a Holy Sister</hi> in their <hi>Travels,</hi> to propagate their <hi>Gospel</hi> in <hi>Foreign Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Expedients,</hi> say they, we must needs have to secure the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> otherwise the <hi>Nation</hi> will be at length pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon to return from whence they came, and once more to observe the <hi>Souldiers</hi> posture, <hi>As you were.</hi> I wish in the mean time we had an <hi>effectual Expedient</hi> to Cure some <hi>Peoples brains</hi> of <hi>Maggots</hi> and <hi>Chimera's,</hi> who seem to tremble with <hi>fear,</hi> where there is no <hi>possibility</hi> of <hi>Danger.</hi> Our <hi>Religion,</hi> I am sure, is already as well secur'd, and as firmly establish'd by the <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Vigilance</hi> of our <hi>Ancestors,</hi> as the <hi>Law</hi> is able to make it, or <hi>human wit</hi> can devise; there being so many severe <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi> in force against all its <hi>Opposers,</hi> even to the making it<note n="*" place="margin">23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. Sect. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Jac.</hi> 4. Sect. 22, 23.</note>
               <hi>Treason</hi> to <hi>pervert</hi> or be <hi>perverted,</hi> that no <hi>Power</hi> on Earth, but our <hi>own folly,</hi> can alter or destroy it. Besides, to remove all <hi>Objections,</hi> and satisfie, if possible, the most <hi>scrupulous</hi> amongst us, <hi>His Majesty</hi> that now is, whose <hi>Word</hi> has ever been as <hi>Sacred,</hi> and as <hi>punctually observ'd,</hi> as the most <hi>Solemn Laws</hi> by any of his <hi>Ancestors,</hi> was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously pleas'd, upon the late <hi>Kings</hi> Decease, to declare himself in <hi>Council,</hi> and give us this further <hi>assurance: I shall make it my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to preserve this Government both in Church and State, as it is now by Law established. I know the Principles of the Church of</hi> England <hi>are for Monarchy, and the Members of it have shew'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100905:14"/> Good and Loyal Subjects, therefore I shall always take care to defend and support it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if all these be thought <hi>insufficient,</hi> what new <hi>Expedient</hi> can be found <hi>able</hi> to secure us? If <hi>People</hi> be so base as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, His <hi>Majesty</hi> will regard neither the <hi>Establish'd Laws,</hi> nor <hi>His Royal Word,</hi> nor yet <hi>His undoubted Interest,</hi> to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose shou'd <hi>People</hi> dream any more of <hi>Expedients,</hi> since the <hi>Laws</hi> formerly made are as full and as binding, as any can be fram'd a new. Unless they will offer (and that to be sure is their <hi>aime</hi>) to clip the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> which is already par'd so very near the <hi>quick,</hi> that nothing more can be parted with, without <hi>apparent danger</hi> to the <hi>Monarchy.</hi> And therefore no <hi>honest man,</hi> or which is the same, no true <hi>lover</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> will <hi>approve</hi> of, much less <hi>promote</hi> any thing, that may tend to a further <hi>dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution</hi> of it; none but such as wou'd fain dash both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> one against the other, will offer to <hi>weaken</hi> the <hi>Crown,</hi> on <hi>pretence</hi> to <hi>support</hi> the <hi>Miter;</hi> whereas indeed nothing can secure the <hi>one,</hi> but the <hi>strength</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>other,</hi> which have been always observ'd, like <hi>Hyppocrates his Twins,</hi> to <hi>Laugh</hi> and <hi>Weep, Live</hi> and <hi>Dye</hi> together.</p>
            <p>But 'tis plain, <hi>Religion</hi> is not the Matter in <hi>Question,</hi> nor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> the <hi>Motive</hi> of all these <hi>Frights</hi> and <hi>Apprehensions. World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Interest</hi> is the <hi>Spring</hi> that moves all the <hi>Wheels,</hi> and provided these Men of <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> cou'd but secure in their own Hands all the <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Employments</hi> in the <hi>Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> I am mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally certain, they wou'd not much care what <hi>Mode</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> shou'd be in <hi>Fashion.</hi> For my part, tho' I have as much <hi>reason</hi> perhaps as another to wish, that none shou'd be employ'd in any considerable <hi>Station</hi> amongst us, but the <hi>obedient Sons</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and that I see no manner of <hi>grounds</hi> to fear, while the <hi>Laws</hi> which the <hi>King</hi> has been <hi>graciously</hi> pleas'd to promise, shou'd be the <hi>Rule</hi> of his <hi>Government,</hi> are so strict and severe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all <hi>Dissenters,</hi> there shall be any other advanc'd in this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> whatsoever His <hi>Majesty</hi> may think fit to do, which is no business of ours, in His other <hi>Dominions,</hi> especially in <hi>Ireland,</hi> where it is not only <hi>lawfull,</hi> but perhaps very <hi>necessary</hi> to employ some <hi>Persons</hi> of known <hi>Integrity,</hi> to ballance the <hi>Cromwellians,</hi> and the <hi>ungovernable Fanaticks</hi> there, who (I am told) have rais'd themselves from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to very considerable <hi>Estates</hi> by Fighting for <hi>Oliver,</hi> and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100905:14"/> therefore cannot easily forget the <hi>Principles</hi> nor the <hi>Practice,</hi> which of <hi>Weavers, Coblers,</hi> and other pitiful <hi>Mechanicks,</hi> made them <hi>Esquires, Knights,</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> of that <hi>Realm.</hi> Tho' I say, there is no <hi>Moral Possibility</hi> of any others being prefer'd here, but such as will, at least <hi>seemingly</hi> conform according to <hi>Law;</hi> yet to give you my own thoughts upon that Point, I must tell you, that as I have been always of <hi>Opinion,</hi> that <hi>Honesty</hi> is not only the best <hi>Policy,</hi> but the best <hi>Religion,</hi> it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess'd by all, that <hi>the Honest Man only goes to Heaven;</hi> and as it cannot enter into my Head, how it is <hi>possible</hi> for any to be really <hi>solicitous</hi> about <hi>Religion,</hi> that practises nothing of it in his <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Conversation:</hi> So I cou'd never yet be induc'd to <hi>believe,</hi> it was the <hi>Interest</hi> either of <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi> to make an <hi>outward Profession</hi> of the <hi>establish'd Religion</hi> a <hi>necessary step</hi> to <hi>Preferment.</hi> That indeed with the <hi>Practice</hi> and other <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments</hi> must be always exacted in <hi>Spiritual Promotions;</hi> but <hi>Merit</hi> only and <hi>good Services</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> shou'd, in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, be thought enough to recommend <hi>Candidates</hi> to <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Military Imployments.</hi> And as it is <hi>Demonstrable,</hi> the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> has been very much weakn'd, by making that the <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi> of the <hi>Princes</hi> favour, which neither <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>Kingdom</hi> were a <hi>Straw</hi> the better for; so 'tis plain the <hi>Church</hi> suffer'd extremly by the accession of <hi>thousands</hi> of <hi>Atheists</hi> and <hi>profane Libertines,</hi> who pretended to be of her <hi>Communion</hi> for no other <hi>Reason,</hi> but to qualify themselves for <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Preferments;</hi> by which means, besides the <hi>Opportunity</hi> given to such <hi>ill men</hi> to execute any <hi>Villany</hi> upon an occasion, to the great <hi>hazard</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> many a <hi>well-meaning Christian</hi> was very much <hi>scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliz'd,</hi> and a <hi>Gap</hi> open'd to her <hi>Enemies</hi> to throw all the dirt they cou'd upon the <hi>most primitive Reform'd Church</hi> in the <hi>World.</hi> 'Tis certainly an odd sort of <hi>Policy,</hi> to exclude one that sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliz'd his <hi>Ability</hi> and his <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> for some <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> in <hi>Religious Opinions,</hi> own'd even by ourselves <hi>unnecessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Salvation;</hi> and prefer another that never gave any one <hi>Instance</hi> of either, because he makes no <hi>Conscience</hi> of taking, nor will perhaps of <hi>breaking,</hi> any <hi>Test</hi> or <hi>Oath</hi> that is tender'd him.</p>
            <p>We see the <hi>Politick French Monarch,</hi> tho' <hi>Himself</hi> and the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality</hi> of his <hi>People</hi> are <hi>zealous Papists,</hi> do nevertheless prefer
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100905:15"/> such of his <hi>Protestant Subjects</hi> as he finds deserving, to places of <hi>Trust</hi> and <hi>Profit,</hi> sends them <hi>Envoys</hi> and <hi>Ambassadors</hi> to his <hi>neighbouring Princes,</hi> makes them <hi>Captains</hi> and <hi>Colonels</hi> in his <hi>Army,</hi> and raises them by degrees according to their <hi>Honesty</hi> and <hi>Capacity,</hi> as appears by Monsieur <hi>Schomberg,</hi> whom tho' a <hi>zealous Protestant,</hi> he made <hi>Mareschal</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>General</hi> in his turn, one of the <hi>highest Stations</hi> and of the <hi>greatest Trust</hi> in his whole <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Neither can the <hi>French Papists</hi> be offended at the Advancement of any such, when they consider 'tis but <hi>Equity</hi> and the <hi>undoubted Right</hi> of the <hi>Subject;</hi> because that part of <hi>political Justice,</hi> which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l'd <hi>Distributive,</hi> always makes it a <hi>due Debt</hi> upon the <hi>Prince</hi> to reward his <hi>Subjects</hi> according to their <hi>Deserts,</hi> as the <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative part</hi> does oblige him on the other side to punish <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders</hi> according to their <hi>Demerits;</hi> with this only <hi>Difference,</hi> that he can with much better <hi>Conscience forgive</hi> the one, than <hi>forget</hi> the other.</p>
            <p>Besides, when a <hi>Prince</hi> has several <hi>Factions,</hi> whether <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> in his <hi>Dominions,</hi> as <hi>Protestant</hi> and <hi>Papist, Guelph</hi> and <hi>Gibelline,</hi> which he cannot easily reconcile, 'tis his <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest,</hi> by employing them indifferently according to their <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Loyalty,</hi> to keep the <hi>Ballance</hi> in an equal <hi>Libration;</hi> that while they are at enmity amongst themselves, they shall have no <hi>Aversion</hi> to him, who impartially rewards them in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their <hi>Deserts:</hi> which must needs create such an <hi>Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> betwixt his <hi>Subjects,</hi> that they will strive to outdo each other to serve their <hi>Prince,</hi> to the great <hi>Advantage</hi> of the <hi>Publick;</hi> and every one, instead of depending on the <hi>idle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> of his <hi>Party,</hi> will endeavour to lay a better and a more useful <hi>Foundation,</hi> that of his own <hi>Merit,</hi> to raise him to <hi>Preferment.</hi> Whereas the contrary Practice will slacken the <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Hands</hi> of many an <hi>able Subject,</hi> who thinking themselves oblig'd in <hi>Honour</hi> not to quit their <hi>Party,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in <hi>Conscience</hi> also not to change their Perswasion for <hi>World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Interest;</hi> if they find they are upon that account uncapable of a due <hi>Encouragement,</hi> they will be <hi>remiss</hi> in promoting their <hi>Princes service:</hi> For it is always observ'd, that <hi>Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward are the great Motives to Zeal and Diligence for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick;</hi> few being now-a-days of the old <hi>Philosophers</hi> temper, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100905:15"/> to love <hi>Vertue</hi> for it self; and therefore the <hi>Poet</hi> was very much in the Right, when he said, <hi>Quis enim Virtutem amplectitur ipsam, Praemia si tollas?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ay, sayes one, but if that were once allow'd, the Protestant Religion wou'd soon decay, and People turn Papists, in great Numbers. A good riddance of them, say I; for 'tis plain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing cou'd be more the <hi>Interest</hi> of the <hi>Establish'd Church,</hi> than to be quit of all her <hi>Counterfeit Members,</hi> who follow <hi>Christ for the Loaves;</hi> because <hi>of all Enemies the pretended Friend is the most dangerous.</hi> Since therefore<note n="*" place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo aestimet bonos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sse de Ecclesia dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere: Triticum non rapit ventus, nec ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rem s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> radice sun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atam proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> subvert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaetempestate jactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. S. <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </note> no <hi>True</hi> or <hi>Real Protestant,</hi> none but <hi>Libertines</hi> and <hi>dissembling Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists</hi> wou'd desert the <hi>Churches Communion</hi> in the Case suppos'd; where is the <hi>Harm,</hi> if that <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> were remov'd, and the wither'd unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Branches</hi> left to fall off by Degrees? Such as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist upon this <hi>Objection,</hi> I am sure, are either silly <hi>Fools</hi> that understand not what they say, or they have the <hi>Jesuits</hi> and the <hi>Dissenters</hi> sence of the <hi>Establish'd Religion,</hi> that it must have <hi>Baits</hi> and <hi>Allurements</hi> to gain <hi>Proselytes;</hi> which is certainly the greatest <hi>Scandal</hi> imaginable upon any <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Perswasion</hi> whatsoever. For Truth will ever prevail, <hi>Magna est veritas &amp; praevalebit;</hi> and tho' it may be <hi>Clouded</hi> for some time, yet it can never be <hi>overcome,</hi> because it alwaies stands firm upon <hi>Feet</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> without any <hi>mixture</hi> of <hi>Clay.</hi> Are not we then extreamly oblig'd to such rare <hi>Advocates,</hi> who seem to plead for the <hi>Establish'd Church,</hi> and with the same <hi>Breath</hi> endeavour to make her <hi>Ridiculous</hi> to her <hi>Enemies?</hi> As if she were not able to stand her <hi>Ground</hi> in <hi>Spirituals,</hi> without a <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nopoly</hi> of all the <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Advantages</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> which (as St. <hi>Jerome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Postquam Ecclesia c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pit Christia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re Magistratus, facta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st quidem opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus maior, sed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus minor. <hi>S. Hierom.</hi>
               </note> has long since well observ'd) does very often ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hinder,</hi> than <hi>advance</hi> the <hi>Purity</hi> of the <hi>Gospel.</hi> Yet this I perceive, is the <hi>ordinary Meth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> of the <hi>Faction,</hi> to make loud <hi>pretences</hi> of <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Church,</hi> and of <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> and at the same time take such <hi>Measures</hi> under this <hi>Mask,</hi> as will effectually <hi>Weaken,</hi> if not <hi>Destroy</hi> both in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Main Point</hi> is yet behind, which if they can but compass by <hi>Hook</hi> or by <hi>Crook,</hi> they are <hi>cock-sure</hi> of the <hi>Victory;</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100905:16"/> but if they shou'd fail, as undoubtedly they will, all their other <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Contrivances</hi> will prove insignificant. The <hi>Revenue</hi> settled on the late <hi>King,</hi> tho very inconsiderable to support the <hi>Grandeur</hi> and the <hi>ordinary Charge</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> has been a great <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> to the <hi>Godly Party,</hi> and no small <hi>Block</hi> in their way to a <hi>tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Reformation,</hi> that is in plain <hi>English,</hi> the <hi>Subversion</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> And therefore they have now all their <hi>Engines</hi> at work to hinder the setling on his present <hi>Majesty</hi> such <hi>Branches</hi> of it, as are not already made <hi>perpetual,</hi> that He may not be able either to defend His <hi>People,</hi> or to offend His <hi>Enemies.</hi> But as the <hi>Devil,</hi> when he intends most <hi>Mischief,</hi> transforms himself into an <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Light,</hi> so do our <hi>giddy Gospellers,</hi> to hide their <hi>Cloven Foot</hi> of <hi>Separation,</hi> pretend to be <hi>zealous Advocates</hi> for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> when really they design Her <hi>Ruine,</hi> which they know has no <hi>Security</hi> under <hi>God,</hi> but in the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</hi> They boast, that besides some <hi>Lords</hi> and several <hi>Commoners</hi> of the <hi>Establish'd Religion,</hi> they have got a <hi>Prelate</hi> or two (and you may remember they allow'd us lately but two <hi>Protestant Bishops</hi>) to joyn with them in their Insolent <hi>Proposal</hi> for <hi>Clipping</hi> the <hi>Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative;</hi> which if refus'd, as they expect it will, because <hi>unreaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> and of very ill <hi>Consequence,</hi> they hope it may then beget such <hi>Misunderstandings</hi> between <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> as will make them part without providing for the <hi>Security</hi> of the <hi>Publick.</hi> Yet because they find the <hi>Nation</hi> is now grown <hi>weary</hi> of <hi>Confusion,</hi> and the <hi>Major Part,</hi> out of a sense of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>common safety,</hi> inclin'd to comply with their <hi>Soveraign</hi> for the support of the <hi>Government,</hi> they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e another <hi>Project,</hi> which they think will <hi>better</hi> take, and in <hi>Process</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> will do their <hi>Work</hi> as well, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Revenue</hi> be not setled but from <hi>Year</hi> to <hi>Year,</hi> at most not above <hi>three Years</hi> together, that they may, like <hi>Dutiful Subjects,</hi> keep their <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> on his <hi>good Behaviour;</hi> by which <hi>Means</hi> they are sure of <hi>frequent opportunities</hi> to shuffle the Cards again, and venture in spite of <hi>Fate</hi> another <hi>Game</hi> for the <hi>Good Old Cause.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These, Sir, are the <hi>wild Imaginations</hi> of a restless sort of <hi>People</hi> amongst us, whose <hi>Religion,</hi> like the <hi>Story</hi> of the <hi>Salamander</hi> in the Fire, never thrieves but in <hi>Confusion.</hi> And therefore I shou'd be sorry, that any <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> whose <hi>Doctrine</hi> I am sure is quite opposite, shou'd be so far misled, as to joyn with them in such <hi>Disloyal Contrivances.</hi> We may easily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100905:16"/> from late and former Experience, that the <hi>Welfare</hi> of all <hi>Nations,</hi> but more particularly of this, wholly consists in a <hi>good Ʋnderstanding,</hi> and <hi>mutual Confidence</hi> between <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People;</hi> and that if the one be <hi>jealous</hi> of the other, neither our <hi>Peace</hi> at home, nor <hi>Trade</hi> abroad can be <hi>Durable;</hi> for both <hi>Domestick</hi> and <hi>Foreign Enemies</hi> will daily gain ground upon us, and make us at length a <hi>Prey</hi> to their <hi>Malice</hi> or <hi>Ambition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, if we consider the <hi>Grievous Complaints</hi> of former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges against <hi>Monopolyes,</hi> and the frequent <hi>Disputes</hi> about the <hi>Kings Prerogative,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> with the <hi>many Evils</hi> that follow'd to the great <hi>Hazard</hi> of the <hi>Publick,</hi> which were all founded on the <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Money,</hi> we shall quickly conclude with the <hi>Emperour Theodosius, Periculosissimum Animal Pauper Rex:</hi> And that it is neither <hi>Dutiful</hi> nor <hi>Prudent</hi> in <hi>Subjects</hi> to tempt their <hi>Prince</hi> to go out of the beaten <hi>Road,</hi> and strain his <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> or hearken to the <hi>Devices</hi> of <hi>Projectors,</hi> for the <hi>support</hi> of his <hi>Government.</hi> His <hi>Majesty</hi> in his most <hi>Gracious Declaration</hi> was pleas'd to take particular notice of the <hi>Loyalty</hi> both of the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> and of the <hi>Principles</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and promis'd upon that Account to defend and support it. But, if in stead of continuing <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Faithful,</hi> according to our <hi>Duty</hi> and to our <hi>Conscience,</hi> we shou'd endeavour by raising a <hi>Faction</hi> in the <hi>State,</hi> to make the <hi>Crown</hi> uneasie, we cancel the <hi>Obligation</hi> of this <hi>Gracious Promise,</hi> and give his <hi>Majesty</hi> occasion to make us as <hi>uneasie</hi> as he pleases. For 'tis manifest, as his <hi>Majesty</hi> well observ'd, <hi>the Laws of England are sufficient to make the King as great a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>narch as he can wish:</hi> And if he were forc'd by the <hi>Baseness</hi> of some <hi>People</hi> to take fuch <hi>Measures</hi> in his own <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> which I am certain, nothing but their <hi>Perversness</hi> cou'd induce him to do, 'tis <hi>Demonstrable,</hi> he cou'd raise more <hi>Money</hi> that way in one year, than he can expect from his <hi>Parliament</hi> in three.</p>
            <p>This cou'd be made out by several <hi>Instances,</hi> yet because I have always been a great <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>Projects,</hi> and very averse from cutting out <hi>new ways</hi> for raising the <hi>King Money,</hi> when a <hi>Parliament,</hi> if mindful of their <hi>Duty</hi> and of the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> is undoubtedly the <hi>Best</hi> and the most <hi>Natural Method,</hi> I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance only two <hi>Branches,</hi> and make no <hi>extravagant Calculation,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:100905:17"/> to prove my <hi>Assertion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 <hi>E.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 19.</note> The first is, that if the * <hi>Laws</hi> made by K. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. and confirm'd by Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and K. <hi>James,</hi> against <hi>eating</hi> of <hi>Flesh</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi> and other <hi>Fasting-days,</hi> were put in <hi>execution,</hi> where the least <hi>Penalty</hi> is ten shillings and ten days <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment</hi> for the first, and double for the <hi>second Offence</hi> (not to mention higher<note n="*" place="margin">5 <hi>Eliz</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35 <hi>EliC. z.</hi> 7. 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 4.</note>
               <hi>Forfeitures</hi> since impos'd) most <hi>People</hi> rather than be obnoxious to such <hi>Penalties,</hi> or oblig'd to abstain from Flesh near 150 days in the Year, two Fifths of the whole, wou'd give a yearly Sum, at least 20 shillings one with another, and save treble by it in the price of Fish, for <hi>Licences</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> according to a <hi>Proviso</hi> made in one of the said Statutes: <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always, and be it ordained and enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That this Act or any thing therein contain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, shall not in any wise extend to any Person or Persons, that hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath, or hereafter shall have obtained any Licence of our Sovereign Lord the King, his Heirs or Successors.</hi> 2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3 Ed. 6. <hi>C.</hi> 19. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. Now all <hi>knowing Men</hi> do generally agree there are in <hi>England</hi> at least <hi>six Millions</hi> of Persons, and we may reasonably suppose above two Fifths liable to this <hi>Statute,</hi> who consequently wou'd yield to the <hi>Crown</hi> two <hi>Millions</hi> and a half of Pounds Sterling <hi>per An.</hi> near double the <hi>Produce</hi> of the three great <hi>Branches</hi> of the <hi>Revenue,</hi> the <hi>Customs, Excise,</hi> and <hi>Hearth Money.</hi> Secondly, If his <hi>Majesty,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> forbid, should find the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> refractory, and thereupon think fit to countenance the <hi>Dissenters,,</hi> and sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> against them, pursuant to the <hi>Bill</hi> pass'd both <hi>Houses</hi> in the last <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Westminster,</hi> he might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave their <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Purses</hi> at his <hi>Devotion,</hi> if it were for no other <hi>Reason,</hi> but to spite the establish'd <hi>Church,</hi> and seem to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utdo them in <hi>Loyalty.</hi> And since there are in <hi>England</hi> above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ix hundred thousand <hi>Dissenters</hi> and <hi>Libertines,</hi> who wou'd ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her pay 12 pence a <hi>Sunday,</hi> that is 52 shillings <hi>per An.</hi> than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e oblig'd to go to <hi>Church;</hi> his <hi>Majesty</hi> might receive above a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illion</hi> and a half more upon this Account.</p>
            <p>Thus I have shew'd you in part, how the <hi>King</hi> might raise <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oney</hi> enough to supply his <hi>Necessities,</hi> without the <hi>Assistance</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a <hi>Parliament;</hi> yet at the same time I must tell you, I do
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100905:17"/> not approve of the <hi>Method,</hi> nor do I believe <hi>his Majesty</hi> will ever make use of any such <hi>Artifice,</hi> who values more a <hi>Penny</hi> with the <hi>Affection</hi> of his <hi>People,</hi> than a <hi>Pound</hi> gain'd by any other <hi>Means.</hi> Nevertheless, it makes it plain, 'tis our <hi>Interest</hi> as well as <hi>Duty,</hi> not to tempt him too much; for if it be a true saying, <hi>Cervus lacessitus Leo,</hi> what shall a <hi>Lyon</hi> be, when provok'd beyond Measure?</p>
            <p>As for that <hi>Factious Contrivance</hi> of the <hi>Cabal,</hi> to have the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue</hi> settled but from year to year, or some limited time, 'tis so <hi>Base</hi> and so <hi>Disloyal</hi> a <hi>Project,</hi> that it is not to be imagin'd the <hi>Parliament</hi> wou'd propose, or the <hi>King</hi> accept of any such thing. 'Tis enough to make all <hi>Honest Men</hi> abhor it, that it was never off r'd to any <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but to his <hi>Majesties Father,</hi> our <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> whom the <hi>Bloodhounds,</hi> that hunted him to the <hi>Scaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld,</hi> thought fit to feed as it were with <hi>Sugar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plums,</hi> till they wheedled him out of all Power, and then made him a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to secure their <hi>Ʋsurpation.</hi> But the <hi>Impudence</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> is very <hi>prodigious,</hi> who have the <hi>Face</hi> to think of such a <hi>Proposal,</hi> and at the same time talk of the <hi>Necessity</hi> of a <hi>general Act</hi> of <hi>Indemnity,</hi> to <hi>forget</hi> and <hi>forgive</hi> all past <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages.</hi> Wou'd it please them, think you, to have such a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> as wou'd secure them from <hi>Justice</hi> from year to year, or from one <hi>Session</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> to another, as they are pleas'd to propose about the <hi>Revenue?</hi> Or wou'd they have the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue</hi> so <hi>Limited,</hi> and the <hi>Pardon</hi> made <hi>Absolute?</hi> This I am sure no <hi>Honest man</hi> will approve of; none, but a <hi>Partie</hi> in the late <hi>Conspiracy</hi> will offer or promote. I am sensible an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion,</hi> provided the <hi>Crown</hi> were secur'd against further Attempts, wou'd be a great Means to quiet <hi>Peoples</hi> minds; whereof a great many are still <hi>Apprehensive,</hi> the <hi>Conspirators,</hi> that fled from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> will one time or other be taken, or freely come in, and to save their own <hi>Bacon,</hi> will discover their Accomplices in that <hi>Hellish Design,</hi> which (as <hi>Captain Walcot</hi> confess'd in his last <hi>Speech</hi> at <hi>Tyburn) was laid very deep, and the King had a great many men to take Judgment of:</hi> But otherwise 'tis only accquitting the <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of all their former <hi>Contrivances,</hi> and exposing the <hi>Monarchy</hi> to their <hi>future Designs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This wou'd be a <hi>Fatal Errour</hi> indeed, and of so pernicious a <hi>Consequence,</hi> that we need not fear there will be any such <hi>Pardon</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100905:18"/> granted, without good <hi>Provision</hi> made on the other side to keep the <hi>Disaffected</hi> in awe. And 'tis manifest there is no <hi>possibility</hi> of providing for, or securing the <hi>Crown,</hi> nor consequently the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquillity</hi> of his <hi>Majesties</hi> good Subjects, any other way than by settling for ever a <hi>sufficient Revenue</hi> for the <hi>Support</hi> and <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> against all the <hi>Machinations</hi> of its <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</hi> For to settle a <hi>fond,</hi> tho otherwise considerable, for a term of years, or during Life, is like the <hi>Jesuits Powder,</hi> which puts the <hi>ill Humors</hi> asleep for some time, but destroys not the <hi>Original Cause</hi> of the Distemper. And if we consider that the <hi>Nation</hi> wou'd think it less grievous, to be tax'd yearly a <hi>Million</hi> of <hi>Money</hi> for seven years together, than oblig'd to pay four <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions</hi> in any one year, without being charg'd a Farthing for the other six, because the former operates like <hi>Physical Dyet,</hi> but the later like a <hi>Violent Purgation,</hi> we shall find 'tis no less the <hi>Peoples</hi> than the <hi>Princes</hi> Interest to have the Revenue made certain and perpetual. It was well observ'd by the best <hi>Parliament</hi> that ever met in our Days, <hi>That nothing conduceth more to the Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity of a Nation, and the Protection of every single Person therein, than that the Publick Revenue thereof may be in some measure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to the Publick Charge and Expence.</hi> 13 &amp; 14 Car. 2. Cap. 10. Sect. 1. Since therefore the <hi>Charges</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> are for the most part <hi>perpetual,</hi> is it not the <hi>undoubted Interest</hi> of all Honest Men, and particularly of those that have any thing to lose, to allow and settle upon the <hi>Crown</hi> for ever such a <hi>proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Revenue,</hi> as may secure them in the peaceable <hi>Possession</hi> of the rest? As for the present, 'tis our <hi>Comfort,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>Mercy</hi> has been pleas'd to set a <hi>Prince</hi> to reign over us, so extraordinarily qualified for the greatest <hi>Ʋndertakings,</hi> that we may well conclude, <hi>He was born to retrieve the sinking Glory of the English Nation,</hi> in whom the <hi>Prudence</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh, and the <hi>Courage</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, without the Dross, either of the <hi>formers</hi> close <hi>Parcimony,</hi> or of the <hi>laters</hi> too much <hi>Severity,</hi> do meet in <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection:</hi> So that in His Days notwithstanding all the <hi>Snarlings</hi> of an <hi>inveterate</hi> sort of <hi>People,</hi> we need not fear any considerable <hi>Disturbance.</hi> But if it please <hi>God</hi> to call him, which I heartily wish may not be till after a <hi>Long</hi> and <hi>Prosperous Reign,</hi> from an <hi>Earthly</hi> to a <hi>Heavenly Crown,</hi> and leave no <hi>Issue Male,</hi> or but a <hi>Child</hi> to succeed him, what shall then become of the <hi>Monarchy,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100905:18"/> if at the same time the greatest part of the <hi>Revenue</hi> happens to expire? The <hi>people</hi> will dwindle afresh into several <hi>Parties</hi> and <hi>Factions,</hi> the <hi>Republicans</hi> have an opportunity to push for their <hi>Darling Commonwealth,</hi> and the <hi>Crown</hi> because poor, and the <hi>Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor</hi> not very active, will be in danger of being made a <hi>Prey</hi> by the <hi>strongest Arm</hi> and <hi>longest Sword;</hi> which will inevitably turn our <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish Paradise</hi> into a <hi>Field</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> and involve the three <hi>Kingdoms</hi> in endless Confusions.</p>
            <p>To prevent therefore such <hi>Fatal Calamities,</hi> as I do not question your <hi>Zeal</hi> in the Matter, so I hope your <hi>Fellow-Members,</hi> and the whole <hi>Representative Wisdom</hi> of the <hi>Nation, King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> will take effectual care to secure your <hi>Country,</hi> not only in your <hi>own days,</hi> but as far as <hi>possible,</hi> for <hi>Future Generations.</hi> If you consider, how stiff and unreasonably <hi>obstinate People</hi> are sometimes, who like the <hi>Foolish Members</hi> in the <hi>Apologue</hi> combining against the <hi>Belly,</hi> refuse to help their <hi>Prince,</hi> tho' to prevent their own and their <hi>Countries</hi> ruine, you can have no <hi>Reason</hi> to leave a busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of such <hi>Importance,</hi> as the <hi>Welfare</hi> of your <hi>Posterity,</hi> to <hi>blind chance,</hi> or to the <hi>Humor</hi> and <hi>Capricio</hi> of <hi>pretended Patriots.</hi> The taking of <hi>Constantinople</hi> by <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great gives us a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>instance</hi> of this sort of <hi>Madness,</hi> which made the <hi>Grecians</hi> of a <hi>Learned flourishing Nation,</hi> become the most <hi>ignorant Peasants,</hi> and the <hi>veriest Slaves</hi> in Nature. The poor <hi>Emperor</hi> went, as it were for <hi>Alms</hi> from door to door, begging of the <hi>Rich Citizens</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute a little <hi>Money</hi> to enable him against the <hi>Common Enemy:</hi> but they pleaded <hi>Poverty,</hi> and wou'd not part with a <hi>Farthing,</hi> till the <hi>Town</hi> was taken by Storm, and <hi>three hundred Millions</hi> of their <hi>Money</hi> brought into the <hi>Conquerors</hi> Coffers; who wondering how so Rich a <hi>City</hi> cou'd be so easily won, said, <hi>If these People had bestow'd but three Millions of this Money in defence of their City, I cou'd never have taken it.</hi> But what need we go into <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countries,</hi> when we have <hi>instances</hi> enough at <hi>Home,</hi> and within our own <hi>Memory,</hi> to convince us of this Truth. The strange <hi>usage King CHARLES</hi> the first, and his late <hi>Majesty</hi> for some years past, receiv'd from an <hi>ungrateful sort of People,</hi> (who the more <hi>Gracious</hi> and <hi>obliging</hi> they found their <hi>Prince,</hi> the more <hi>Stiff</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory</hi> still they grew, to the undoing almost of the whole <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) is <hi>warning</hi> enough to all honest and thinking <hi>Men,</hi> to provide against such dangerous <hi>Fits</hi> of <hi>Madness</hi> for the future.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100905:19"/>
            <p>'Tis true, saies one, it were to be wish'd such provisions cou'd be made, as wou'd for ever secure the <hi>Crown</hi> from all future Attempts both <hi>Forreign</hi> and <hi>Domestick;</hi> but then, on the other side, what se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity cou'd the <hi>People</hi> have, that the <hi>Prince</hi> wou'd not in two or three Generations shake off his <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and make Himself <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute?</hi> This, I must confess, is a very <hi>Popular Objection,</hi> and the main <hi>Block</hi> in our way to a <hi>Happy Settlement,</hi> which is never to be hop'd for without a mutual Confidence between <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> yet we see, it weigh'd not with the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whose steady <hi>Loyalty</hi> in the late times of <hi>Tryal,</hi> and now in making the <hi>Revenue</hi> of that Kingdom <hi>Perpetual,</hi> has made all possible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the many Evils the <hi>Scotch Covenant</hi> has formerly brought upon us. And I hope, it shall never be said, that an <hi>English Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> will be behind them in <hi>Duty</hi> or <hi>Affection</hi> to their <hi>Prince,</hi> or less mindful of the <hi>Publick;</hi> especially when they can have no other grounds for so doing, but bare unsupposable possibilities of future Inconveniences. For it is not to be imagin'd by <hi>Rational</hi> Men, that any <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> will ever be so far overseen, as to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the loss of all the hearts of his <hi>People,</hi> the only <hi>support</hi> and <hi>security</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> to make himself somewhat more <hi>absolute,</hi> while He may, even by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> be as great a <hi>Monarch</hi> as any good <hi>Christian</hi> can wish; and the frequent <hi>Meetings</hi> and <hi>Counsels</hi> of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> are the only means to make both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Happy;</hi> because, as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Without Counsel, Purposes are disappointed, but in the multitude of Counsellours they are established.</hi> Prov. 15.22.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, to obviate this and all other Objections of that kind, if we seriously consider Matters, we shall find that a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle course may be taken, by which we may avoid all these In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences. For if a competent <hi>Revenue,</hi> that is, the <hi>Customs</hi> and the temporary part of the <hi>Excise,</hi> be made perpetual, to support the <hi>Crown</hi> against <hi>Forreign</hi> or <hi>Domestick Designs,</hi> upon the Death of the <hi>Sovereign;</hi> And because this is not sufficient to defray the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary <hi>Charges</hi> of the <hi>Government,</hi> while our <hi>Neighbours</hi> have far great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> settle an <hi>Additional Fond</hi> for Life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100905:19"/> every three years, otherwise all farther <hi>Levies</hi> of the same to cease; both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> will then be secur'd, <hi>Parliaments</hi> even upon this account will be found still necessary, the <hi>Nation</hi> much eas'd in raising their <hi>Taxes,</hi> and the <hi>Crown</hi> made more considerable both at home and abroad.</p>
            <p>You will excuse me, I hope, if I do not any further descend to Particulars, or take upon me to tell you exactly, which your Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Members can do a great deal better, how much may be a sufficient Fond to answer all the ends aforemention'd. 'Tis enough to say in general, that I see no other Rule in that Case to be made use of, but the Consideration of the Strength and Riches of our Neighbour-Nations, and that the Publick <hi>Revenue</hi> of <hi>England</hi> must bear some proportion to theirs, unless we intend to live within ourselves, and think no longer on trading with Forreign Countries. We see how much the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> have, within these fourscore years past, encroach'd upon our undoubted Right, the Dominion of the Narrow Seas, and by that upon our Trade and Commerce, the great Magazine of our Wealth, to the loss of many Millions a year to the <hi>English</hi> Nation. And we cannot in reason expect they will desist, untill we put ourselves into such a posture, as will make it visible to the World, we are able to cope with them, and to recover our own; which yet is altogether impossible, as long as we have nothing else to depend upon, but temporary Taxes, to carry on a War; while they have vast Sums of Money in Cash, and a large yearly <hi>Revenue</hi> to oppose us, the <hi>French King</hi> about twelve Millions of Pounds sterling <hi>per an.</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> time stil'd themselves, <hi>The poor distressed States of Holland,</hi> above five Millions, coming in yearly into their publick Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury. For they cannot be ignorant, but that the extraordinary Charge of a War, falling upon us all of a sudden, will quickly make the <hi>People</hi> here so uneasie, that they will be content to quit their Right after all their losses, and clap up a Peace on any terms, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than bear such heavy unusual Taxes any longer; so that if our Enemies can but prolong the War for some years, they will by degrees weary us out, and force us at last to a Compliance. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100905:20"/>
            <p>But because the Circulation of Money is thought as necessary to the <hi>Body Politick,</hi> as that of Blood to the <hi>Natural,</hi> and therefore the hoarding up such Sums in time of Peace wou'd prove very prejudicial to Trade, the Life and Vigour of a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> this intended Bank of Money may still be laid out to use on good Securities by <hi>Commissioners</hi> appointed by Act of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> some of the most knowing, most honest, and best estated of both Houses, and the Interest constantly imploy'd either in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Work-houses</hi> for the <hi>Strong,</hi> and <hi>Hospitals</hi> for the <hi>Sick</hi> and <hi>Disabled Poor</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or in some publick Trade, as the <hi>Woollen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture, Fishing,</hi> or the like, which will be of infinite Advantage to the whole Body of the <hi>Nation.</hi> Neither is it it to be reckon'd the least, that this Method wou'd in a short time spoil the sport of <hi>upstart cheating Bankers,</hi> who stick like Leeches daily sucking the Blood of the credulous unwary People, while they can find any faith upon earth; but when that fails them, so that they can suck no more, then they drop off, and to the ruine of hundreds of poor families wilfully break for many thousands of Pounds, tho perhaps not one of them had a hundred to begin withal, and run into the <hi>Fryers</hi> or the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> where they live like petty Princes upon the Fortunes of poor Widows and Orphans, to whom in case they condescend to come to any Composition, they will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allow a Crown in the Pound of their Principal Money. And which is very strange, there is no <hi>Corporal Punishment</hi> here, as in <hi>Foreign Countries,</hi> not so much as the Pillory to be inflicted in this <hi>Case,</hi> nor any other Remedy to be had, if the Bankrupt has the wit to secure his Books and Money, which he may easily do, when he <hi>designedly</hi> breaks to defraud his Creditors.</p>
            <p>This is a hard case indeed, and a very great grievance, well worth the <hi>Parliaments Care</hi> to contrive such Laws as may prevent the like for the future; But the <hi>Devil of Perjury</hi> is the grand <hi>Grievance</hi> of all, which best deserves their most serious Consideration: For if such as deal with Bankrupts are <hi>ruin'd</hi> in their <hi>Estates,</hi> and if upon that account others are frightned from laying out their Money, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause for a <hi>little Gain</hi> they will not <hi>hazard</hi> the loss of their whole <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> which is a main obstruction to Trade; the <hi>True-Protestant Flayl</hi> of <hi>Perjury</hi> will not only ruine <hi>People</hi> in their <hi>Fortunes,</hi> but will <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> them out of their <hi>Innocence,</hi> and sweep <hi>Estate, Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Life</hi> and all away, to the uttter undoing of whole <hi>Families.</hi> Yet
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100905:20"/> certainly 'tis a great Solecism in our Laws, that if one <hi>Robs</hi> another of <hi>Sixpence</hi> upon the Road, he is hang'd without any more ado; but if a Banker <hi>cheats thousands</hi> of his Majesties Subjects, of <hi>Millions of Money,</hi> and can but get into the <hi>Fryers</hi> or <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> he is as safe as a Thief in a Mill, and cares not a straw whether his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors do live or starve. And which is yet worse, if a forsworn Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain will set up for a <hi>Kings</hi> Evidence, and by his Perjuries murder never so many innocent Subjects, all he is to suffer, is to stand in the Pillory, or lose his <hi>more harmless Ears,</hi> instead of his <hi>Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Tongue.</hi> Whereas the Divine Law expresly orders, that <hi>Whosoever sheddeth mans blood, by man shall his blood be shed,</hi> Gen. 9.6.</p>
            <p>But the Truth is, tho' the Fundamentals of our Constitutions be undoubtedly the best Laws in the world, and the most suitable to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Nation; yet we have several defects on the one hand, and a great deal of rubbish on the other, that want a Reformation, the proper province of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi> And in this case, as I am certain of your Zeal, so I doubt not but your Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Members will be forward enough to promote so good a Work, whereon the happiness of this Nation so much depends, which some of their Predecessors have strangely neglected. For I find the <hi>French Gentleman</hi> was not very much out in his Observation, when he said, that as the <hi>Roman</hi> Conclave's overbusying themselves with Temporal Matters and State-Affairs, which was none of their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness, did no small injury to the Christian Religion; so several Members of our House of Commons for some years past, medling too much with Religion, and prying into Intrigues of State, which was quite out of their<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>35</hi> Eliz. The Queen herself told the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, It was not meant they shou'd meddle with matters of State, or Causes Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. And the like did K. <hi>James 1. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dersons</hi> Hist. <hi>p. 510.</hi>
               </note> Sphere, made them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much neglect the true Interest of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. But now, I hope, we have got a true English Parliament, that will zealously promote the Good of the Publick, disable the Faction from making any disturbance, settle a sufficient Revenue upon the Crown, to support the Grandeur and necessary Charge of the Government, repeal the useless and enact new Laws for the advancement of Trade, and in a word, make their King as happy in this, as ever any of his Ancestors have been in their most Loyal and bountiful Parliaments: Which, because the only way to a <hi>Lasting Settlement,</hi> is the hearty wish of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>7. <hi>May</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>